<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/mUlAni/mahAbhAShyam/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/mUlAni/mahAbhAShyam/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Joshi on patanjali</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/mUlAni/mahAbhAShyam/articles/joshi_on_patanjali/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/mUlAni/mahAbhAShyam/articles/joshi_on_patanjali/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Joshi and Roodbergen left their Mahabhashya project unfinished after 12 volumes (11/85 āhnikas) with this comment:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we started the Mahabhaṣya-project, our idea was that it could be only through Patanjali that we would be able to understand Panini better. How- ever, we have now come to the conclusion that, apart from introducing a great deal of extraneous material in the interpretation of the Paninisutras, Patanjali is often at a loss to construe Panini&amp;rsquo;s intention. Therefore Patanjali can only act as a guide to be critically followed, not as the final authority with respect to Panini. The Mahabhaṣya can never replace one&amp;rsquo;s independent judgment regarding the interpretation of Panini, especially in the matter of anuvṛtti and nivṛtti of rules, and of conflict-solving procedures. We have also come to the conclusion that, to some extent, the Käsikävṛtti has preserved an authentic grammgtical tradition, independent of and different from Patanjali.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>दासगुप्त-सुरेन्द्रनाथः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/mUlAni/mahAbhAShyam/articles/dAsagupta-surendranAthaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/mUlAni/mahAbhAShyam/articles/dAsagupta-surendranAthaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;of-what-words-of-the-popular-and-the-vedic-there-the-popular-are-the-cow-the-horse-the-man-the-elephant-the-bird-the-beast-the-brahmin-and-so-forth-also-there-are-the-vedic-propositions-as-illustrated-in-the-atharvan-yajus-rc-and-saman--sanno-devir-abhiṣṭaye&#34;&gt;ICPR TRANSLATION OF&#xA;Indian Philosophical&#xA;Classics&#xA;General Editor: Sibajiban Bhattacharyya&#xA;The Mahabhaṣya of Patanjali&#xA;SURENDRANATH&#xA;DASGUPTA&#xA;ICPR TRANSLATION OF INDIAN 25122 PHILOSOPHICAL CLASSICS&#xA;THE MAHABHAṢYA OF PATANJALI&#xA;ICPR TRANSLATION OF INDIAN PHILOSOPHICAL CLASSICS&#xA;GENERAL EDITOR&#xA;Sibajiban Bhattacharyya&#xA;ADVISORY BOARD&#xA;Badarinath Shukla (deceased) Visva Bandhu Bhattacharyya K. Kunjunni Raja&#xA;R. Balasubramanian&#xA;THE MAHABHAṢYA OF PATANJALI&#xA;WITH ANNOTATIONS&#xA;(ĀHNIKAS I-IV)&#xA;SURENDRANATH DASGUPTA&#xA;Edited by&#xA;SIBAJIBAN BHATTACHARYYA&#xA;jor&#xA;INDIAN COUNCIL OF PHILOSOPHICAL RESEARCH. NEW DELHI&#xA;First Published 1991&#xA;H&#xA;Indian Council of Philosophical Research 1991&#xA;All rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced in any form, or by any means, without written permission of the publisher.&#xA;Published by the Member Secretary for&#xA;INDIAN COUNCIL OF PHILOSOPHICAL RESEARCH Rajendra Bhavan (Fourth Floor), 210 Deen Dayal Upadhaya Marg New Delhi 110002&#xA;Distributed by&#xA;MUNSHIRAM MANOHARLAL PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD. 54 Rani Jhansi Road, New Delhi 110055&#xA;ISBN: 81-215-0530-3&#xA;Typeset by Neographics&#xA;Trade Centre, 2/7 Ansari Road, Darya Ganj, New Delhi 110 002&#xA;Printed at Rajkamal Electric Press&#xA;B-35/9 G.T. Karnal Road, Delhi 110 033&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;Editor&amp;rsquo;s Preface&#xA;FIRST AHNIKA (Paspaśā)&#xA;vii&#xA;1&#xA;SECOND AHNIKA&#xA;65&#xA;THIRD AHNIKA&#xA;135&#xA;FOURTH AHNIKA&#xA;213&#xA;Index&#xA;251&#xA;EDITOR&amp;rsquo;S PREFACE&#xA;Dr (Mrs) Surama Dasgupta donated a collection of unpublished works of the late Dr Surendranath Dasgupta to the library of the Indian Council of Philosophical Research, Lucknow. The present work belongs to that collection.&#xA;The work as published here is incomplete in two ways. Firstly, it covers only the first four Ahnikas of Prathamâdhyaya of the Mahabhaṣya. Secondly, even of the four Ahnikas, the second and fourth Ahnikas are incomplete. There were two possible courses open here. First, to get the incomplete Ahnikas completed and to append them to the main work. This way was not followed because of the following reason. The value of the present work lies not so much in the translation of the text but in the very thorough discussions on all topics in the annotations. It was felt that a comparable treatment of the portions left out by Dr Dasgupta could be given only by someone having the width and depth of knowledge of the subject which Dr Dasgupta had. As such a scholar was not readily available, on the advice of Mrs Dasgupta the work is published in the same form in which Dr Dasgupta left it. As Dr. Dasgupta dictated different parts of the manuscript to different scholars apparently of unequal competence, the manuscript contained many errors of different sorts. I thank the editorial reader, Pandit Satkari Mukhopadhyaya of Sahitya Akademi, New Delhi, for carefully going through the manuscript, correcting mis- takes which remained after my editing, and for preparing the index. We have, however, corrected only obvious mistakes in spelling and in grammar.&#xA;It is hoped that this great work, incomplete though it is, will attract attention not merely of scholars of Sanskrit grammar, but also of philos- ophers of language because of the important philosophical discussions on various topics in the annotations.&#xA;April, 1991&#xA;SIBAJIBAN BHATTACHARYYAFIRST AHNIKA (Paspaśā)&#xA;Panini.&#xA;atha sabdânuśāsanam&#xA;Bhāṣya.&#xA;athety ayam sabdo&amp;rsquo; dhikārārthaḥ prayujyate. śabdanuśāsanam nama śāstram adhikrtam veditavyam.&#xA;The object of grammar is directly specified here by the elaborator of grammar, Patanjali - &amp;lsquo;atha&amp;rsquo; etc. Now (follows) the instruction of words. The word &amp;lsquo;atha&amp;rsquo; is used to indicate the commencement of the topic. Though the topic of the instruction of words is a long process, the word &amp;lsquo;atha&amp;rsquo; indicates the commencement of such a topic. The action of instruction has for its object, &amp;rsquo;the words&amp;rsquo;. The word &amp;lsquo;adhikara&amp;rsquo; means prastava or the commencement of a topic.1&#xA;Bhāṣya.&#xA;keṣām sabdānām? laukikānām vaidikānām ca. tatra laukikās tāvad gaur aśvaḥ puruşo&#xA;hasti sakunirmṛgo brāhmaṇa iti. vaidikāḥ&#xA;khalvapi - śam no devir abhiṣṭaye; işe&#xA;tvorje tva; agnim ile purohitam; agna āyāhi vitaya iti.&#xA;Of what words? Of the popular and the Vedic. There the popular are: the cow, the horse, the man, the elephant, the bird, the beast, the brahmin and so forth. Also there are the Vedic (propositions as illustrated in the Atharvan, Yajus, Rc and Saman)- sanno devir abhiṣṭaye&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;may the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
