<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;उच्चारणम् on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/svaritaH/uchchAraNam/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;उच्चारणम् on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/svaritaH/uchchAraNam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>स्वनिर्णयः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/svaritaH/uchchAraNam/svanirNayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/svaritaH/uchchAraNam/svanirNayaH/</guid>
      <description>वर्तमान-परम्परा उच्चरणविषये स्खलिताश् चेदपि, तदनुसरणे रक्षणे वा जनानाम् अधिकारम् अभ्युपगच्छामि। अष्टाध्याय्याश् च &amp;ldquo;पाणिनिय&amp;quot;शिक्षाग्रन्थस्य च मध्ये विवादे सति, अष्टाध्यायीम् एव प्रमाणं मन्ये – न पश्चाल् लिखितं शिक्षाग्रन्थम्। अत्रौद्धत्यं चेद् दृश्यते, क्षन्तव्योऽहम् – अत्र भवादृशैः परीक्षा, खण्डनमण्डने, परिष्कारश् चैवेष्यन्ते ।  अष्टाध्यायिव्यवस्थापक्षे Basic appeal of the pANinIya system
 An effort to revive and use the pANini’s svara system in veda and loka may be compared with Dr padmA subrahmanyan’s successful fairly revival of &amp;ldquo;mArga-nRtya&amp;rdquo; using bharata-muni’s texts and temple sculptures (&amp;ldquo;bharata&amp;quot;nATya wasn’t good enough).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>स्वरव्यवस्थापर्याये कारणम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/svaritaH/uchchAraNam/svaravyavasthAparyAye_kAraNam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/svaritaH/uchchAraNam/svaravyavasthAparyAye_kAraNam/</guid>
      <description>Why did the svara-vyavasthA that deviated fromthe aShTAdhyAyI system thrive at the cost of the latter? Possible reasons:
 When the svara-s had (mostly) fallen out of use in laukika speech, the simpler thing to teach youngsters, even if it is completely artificial, thrived.&amp;ldquo;Listen boys – anudaatta is lower tone, udaatta is higher tone, svarita is even higher. simple. no falling tone business. now get to memorization.&amp;rdquo; Better marketing strategy. Certain shiShTa-s who had noticed the deviation from pANinidevised various easily accessible and well marketed shikShA texts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
