<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 1 Introduction to the Aṣṭādhyāyī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_1_Introduction_to_the_aShTAdhyAyI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_1_Introduction_to_the_aShTAdhyAyI/</guid>
      <description>Pāṇini1 composed the Aṣṭādhyāyī around 350 BC2 in North-Western South Asia.3 The Aṣṭādhyāyī is a samāhāra ‘collection’ of aṣṭa(n) ‘eight’ adhyāyas ‘books’, hence the name Aṣṭa-adhyāy(a)-ī. Each book of the Aṣṭādhyāyī has four pādas ‘chapters’ that are made up of sūtras ‘rules’. In all, the Aṣṭādhyāyī comprises about 4000 rules. The Aṣṭādhyāyī is a comprehensive grammar of the Sanskrit language as known to its author Pāṇini. It stands out for doing more than merely describing its object language: the Aṣṭādhyāyī is a full-fledged machine which helps construct grammatically correct Sanskrit words and sentences through a step-by-step derivation4 process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 2 Metarules in the Pāṇinian Grammatical Tradition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_2_Metarules_in_the_pANinian_Grammatical_Traditio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_2_Metarules_in_the_pANinian_Grammatical_Traditio/</guid>
      <description>[[11]]
Early grammatical thought in the Indian subcontinent, as represented by the works called Prātiśākhyas, was intended to assist the recitation of Vedas by explaining the pronunciation of accents and dissolution of sandhis. Their objective was merely descriptive, that is, to make grammatical observations and offer clarifications where necessary. But a number of independent and full-fledged grammars emerged subsequently which sought to ‘derive’ language rather than simply ‘describe’ it: they built mechanistic systems which perform various operations on bases and affixes in order to produce correct word forms and, using these fully derived words, to construct meaningful sentences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 3 Modern Perspectives on the Functioning of the Aṣṭādhyāyī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_3_Modern_Perspectives_on_the_Functioning_of_the/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_3_Modern_Perspectives_on_the_Functioning_of_the/</guid>
      <description>Purpose of vyākaraṇam Before we explore how modern scholarship perceives the Aṣṭādhyāyī, let us very briefly consider what the tradition, and more specifically Kātyāyana and Patañjali say, about the meaning and purpose of vyākaraṇa. In vt. 14 of the Paspaśāhnika1, Kātyāyana says: lakṣya-lakṣaṇe vyākaraṇam ‘grammar (stands for the combination of) lakṣya i.e., words (and sentences)’ and lakṣaṇa ‘rules’. This is true of any grammar, not just the Aṣṭādhyāyī. But does the Aṣṭādhyāyī have certain mechanistic properties which set it apart from conventional grammars?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 4 The Traditional View on Rule Conflict</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_4_The_Traditional_View_on_Rule_Conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_4_The_Traditional_View_on_Rule_Conflict/</guid>
      <description>As will be shown in chapter 6, the views of the tradition have gradually evolved on the topic of rule conflict. But here, I shall introduce the topic by outlining those ideas on rule conflict that today’s traditional scholars hold true. To achieve this, I will present the views of the Kāśikā and paribhāṣā texts on this topic. 1.4.2 vipratiṣedhe paraṁ kāryam is the only metarule in the Aṣṭādhyāyī which explicitly deals with rule conflict.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 5 Analysis of the Traditional Perspective</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_5_Analysis_of_the_Traditional_Perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_5_Analysis_of_the_Traditional_Perspective/</guid>
      <description>Let us look at 1.4.2 &amp;ldquo;vipratiṣedhe paraṁ kāryam&amp;rdquo; again. Pāṇini does not explain the meaning of vipratiṣedha in the Aṣṭādhyāyī. The Kāśikā claims that vipratiṣedha means tulyabalavirodha ‘conflict between two equally powerful rules.’ This is a plausible assumption because, in Sanskrit literature, the term has been used to mean ‘the opposition of two courses of action which are equally important, the conflict of two even-matched interests’1. But which conflicts qualify as tulyabala ‘having equal strength’?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 6 Modern Scholarship on 1 4 2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_6_Modern_Scholarship_on_1_4_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_6_Modern_Scholarship_on_1_4_2/</guid>
      <description>The tradition thinks that 1.4.2 applies to tulyabala conflicts between any two rules of the Aṣṭādhyāyī. But many modern scholars, starting with Faddegon (1936), have tried to restrict the scope of 1.4.2 further, to include only those rules that lie between 1.4.2 and 2.2.38: they argue that since 1.4.2 lies within the ekā saṁjñā adhikāra (cf. 1.4.1 ā kaḍārād ekā saṁjñā ‘up to 2.2.38 kaḍārāḥ karmadhāraye, each item can take only one saṁjñā’), the jurisdiction of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 7 My Opinion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_7_My_Opinion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/01/1_7_My_Opinion/</guid>
      <description>In my view, firstly, Pāṇini did not expect us to create the categories ‘tulyabala’ and ‘atulyabala’. Secondly, I think that he taught 1.4.2 as a metarule which, rather than being restricted to a particular section of the Aṣṭādhyāyī, is applicable to the entire Aṣṭādhyāyī.
More broadly, I do not agree with both the traditional and the modern perspectives towards this topic, because instead of trying to decipher the actual meaning of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
