<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bower manuscript story</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/bower_manuscript_story/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/bower_manuscript_story/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
A 19th Century Murder that Excavated a Second-Century Sanskrit Manuscript: Episode One How the brutal murder of a 19th century British trader led to the unlikely discovery of a valuable 2nd century Sanskrit Manuscript. A Murder that Unearthed a Second-Century Sanskrit Manuscript: Episode 1
— 1 —
WHAT BEGAN AS AN ARGUMENT between two businessmen led to the murder of one of them and launched a manhunt against the murderer and culminated in the accidental discovery of a 2nd Century CE Sanskrit manuscript that rattled the world of Indology in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kausambi lament</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/kausAmbi_lament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/kausAmbi_lament/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
At a very conservative estimate, there exist today some 3000 MSS of Bhartṛhari. Most of these, being hidden away in private collections, will be destroyed unused by the action of time, air, rain, mice, white ants and all other vermin except scholars.
The greatest factor that prevents this material from becoming useful is the sloth and negligence of their owners, who rarely know what they possess but are even more rarely willing to have their collections examined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nmm-stats</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/nmm-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/nmm-stats/</guid>
      <description>Source: bhAratendu on TW
Some stats on the manuscripts in India, basis the data published by National Mission of Manuscripts. There are 5 million+ MSS so far catalogued, in public and private collections of India.
While the MSS are in 100+ languages, these 21 account for 90% of MSS
 Sanskrit - 2,389,016 Odiya - 516,501 Hindi - 329,124 Tibetan - 283,668 Tamil - 179,815 Malayalam - 142,818 Kannada - 102,242 Rajasthani - 99,066 Persian - 98,482 Arabic - 92,591 Prakrit - 76,650 Urdu - 71,594 Gujarati - 52,055 Marathi - 44,593 Bengali - 39,917 Assamese - 38,294 Telugu - 26,342 Braja - 10,862 Punjabi - 7,103 Maithili - 6,052 Awadhi - 4,365  These MSS are also written in more than 100 distinct scripts, but these 18 account for 90% of all the MSS so far catalogued.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pANDurangI article</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/pANDurangI-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/pANDurangI-article/</guid>
      <description>A young Sanskrit scholar used to wait patiently on the banks of a river on solar or lunar eclipse days or on festive days hoping that somebody would throw into the river rare and ancient Sanskrit manuscripts. It is the practice among some Hindu families to offer to the &amp;lsquo;Ganga&amp;rsquo; ancient scripts they have inherited if they felt they could no longer keep them or if there is any illness or difficulty in the house.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suhas-lament</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/suhas-lament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/manuscripts/articles/suhas-lament/</guid>
      <description>Think yourself a Zen person? Visit one of these manuscript libraries to unlock unknown levels of blinding rage 🧵from experience. https://t.co/63gmcgzty1
Clerk asks for letter in triplicate from HoD attested by gazetted officer. You bring it back next day, but library unofficially shuts down on Tuesdays and Thursdays. You are only allowed to photograph 20% of the manuscript. Research requires whole thing? Too bad, you have to copy it by hand.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
