<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Female poets</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/female-poets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/female-poets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.deccanherald.com/opinion/female-poets-in-sanskrit-a-legacy-lost-to-time-3438614&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anusha S Rao&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Last Updated : 09 March 2025, 03:35 IST&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was Women’s Day yesterday, and of course, the usual Whatsapp tributes to women being superheroes and excellent multi-taskers made the rounds – which of course completely ignores what women need and want in India – no female foeticides, no violence against women, being treated as equal citizens, equal opportunities… the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Until then, however, I cannot resist but use the opportunity to talk about female poets in Sanskrit. We have only a handful of female poets in Sanskrit – it has always been an elite language. However, the poems we do have make up in quality what is missing in quantity. I am going to refrain from narrating the stories of Gargi, Maitreyi, or Vachaknavi, since we have heard them mentioned all the time as proof that women had equal status as men in Vedic times. This is obviously not the case, considering that any of us can quickly name over a dozen male sages and scholars mentioned in the Vedas. The very fact that we can barely think of three names – two of which, Gargi and Vachaknavi, probably refer to the same person – should tell us something.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hartzell SD 2018</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/hartzell_SD_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/hartzell_SD_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1053811915006382&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brains of verbal memory specialists show anatomical differences in language, memory and visual systems&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Author links open overlay panelJames F. Hartzell a, Ben Davis a, David Melcher a, Gabriele Miceli a, Jorge Jovicich a, Tanmay Nath b, Nandini Chatterjee Singh b, Uri Hasson a&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Under a Creative Commons &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/&#34;&gt;license&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;open access&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;highlights&#34;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;•&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We compared professional Sanskrit verbal memory specialists and well-matched controls.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;•&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We measured cortical thickness (CT), gray matter density (GM), and gyrification (LGI).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sanskrit effect</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/sanskrit-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/articles/sanskrit-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Neuroscientist Explores the &amp;ldquo;Sanskrit Effect&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MRI scans show that memorizing ancient mantras increases the size of brain regions associated with cognitive function&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By James Hartzell on January 2, 2018&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/a-neuroscientist-explores-the-sanskrit-effect/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A hundred dhoti-clad young men sat cross-legged on the floor in facing rows, chatting amongst themselves. At a sign from their teacher the hall went quiet. Then they began the recitation. Without pause or error, entirely from memory, one side of the room intoned one line of the text, then the other side of the room answered with the next line. Bass and baritone voices filled the hall with sonorous prosody, every word distinctly heard, their right arms moving together to mark pitch and accent. The effect was hypnotic, ancient sound reverberating through the room, saturating brain and body. After 20 minutes they halted, in unison. It was just a demonstration. The full recitation of one of India´s most ancient Sanskrit texts, the Shukla Yajurveda, takes six hours.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
