<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>alphabet vs abiguda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/alphabet_vs_abiguda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/alphabet_vs_abiguda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: nikhil on discord&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also a proponent of Roman transliteration instead of Devanāgarī́, because alphabets are superior (computationally &amp;amp;c.) to abugidas.  If there were an Indian alphabet that were widely used, I&amp;rsquo;d use it instead of Latin, but I&amp;rsquo;m not aware of one that even exists let alone being widely used.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Conceptually: they write consonants and vowels separately, which constitute independent sounds not inherently connected to one another, rather than arbitrarily combining them.  Mitrá and mātr̥ ought to begin with the same glyph, but one begins with मि (with the combining vowel in front of the consonant) while the other begins with मा.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superlocal nAgarI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/superlocal-nAgarI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/superlocal-nAgarI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threader.app/thread/1444937888160956419&#34;&gt;https://threader.app/thread/1444937888160956419&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Devanāgarī&amp;rsquo;s supra-local status has historical roots in the early forms of Nāgarī and its prototypes were often used outside of north India, e.g. a script known as Nandī-nāgarī and other similar northern-style scripts were sporadically used in addition to the local scripts for writing Sanskrit in the Deccan / south India from the 7th century onwards.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Inscriptions in early or proto-forms of Nāgarī are also found outside of India, as far as Sri Lanka, Burma &amp;amp; Indonesia, and the scripts, from which Devanāgarī developed, became a sacred form of writing for Buddhists in East Asia. In this sense Nāgarī does have a special status as a sort of first among the firsts among the Indic scripts. In this way, Nāgarī can be said to have played a role among scripts that is in part analogous to that of languages such as Sanskrit, Persian and English, which at various times have served as lingua franca for the pan-Indic cultural region.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>स्वर-मुद्रासु कस्तूरिः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/svara-mudrAsu_kastUriH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/lekhanam/articles/svara-mudrAsu_kastUriH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1082015032655802368.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A thread on kerala hand gestures or mudras used in vedic chanting. Madhyandina hasta mudras appear to be an independent tradition and is passed over right now.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to Dr. Mannur Jatavedan Nambutiri, ŕṣi vaikhānasa lead by parashurāma formulated the kerala style of japasvara and mātrāsvara for udātta and anudātta vedic svaras.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As per a text &amp;lsquo;madhushiksha&amp;rsquo;, the padapāṭha of Rig veda is attributed to Ravana. This is from a quotation of the text in vedavikr̥tivivaraṇam by shrī P.M. Damidaran Nambutiripad. He also adds while commenting that hastamudrā tradition is explained by Ravana.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
