<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;kAnisetti aniruddh on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/articles/kAnisetti-aniruddh/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;kAnisetti aniruddh on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/articles/kAnisetti-aniruddh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Non innovative</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/articles/kAnisetti-aniruddh/non-innovative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/articles/kAnisetti-aniruddh/non-innovative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit didn’t always drive innovation in ancient India. There are two reasons,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit was seen as the language of divinity, thus the main current of Sanskrit knowledge tended to be conservative, resistant to new developments.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Delhi Chief Minister Rekha Gupta &lt;a href=&#34;https://theprint.in/india/sanskrit-scientific-language-nasa-has-written-papers-on-it-delhi-cm-rekha-gupta/2614904/&#34;&gt;declared&lt;/a&gt; that Sanskrit, ancient India’s premier language of power and literature, is “scientific” and “the most computer-friendly language”, according to “NASA scientists”. This claim has been doing the rounds for over a decade, sometimes accompanied by pseudoscientific declarations of the achievements of ancient Indians—think flying saucers, cloning, nuclear weapons, and whatnot.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-innovative rebuttal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/articles/kAnisetti-aniruddh/non-innovative-rebuttal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/articles/kAnisetti-aniruddh/non-innovative-rebuttal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brhat.in/dhiti/rebuttal-to-print-article-sanskrit-innovation&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rebuttal to The Print’s Article - Sanskrit Didn’t Always Drive Innovation in Ancient India&#xA;A rebuttal to The Print&amp;rsquo;s recent article disparaging the value of Sanskrit in driving innovation in ancient and medieval India.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;18 June, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1891 words&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sai Priya Chodavarapu&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anirudh Kanisetti is back at it again with his nefarious agenda. In his most recent article for The Print, his hatred for Saṃskṛta and his giddy excitement at the chance to tarnish Hinduism is barely veiled (as usual). The premise of his article is that Saṃskṛta is glorified undeservingly, as it incubated a culture resistant to innovation: specifically, he claims that Saṃskṛta bred stagnation in the fields of mathematics and astronomy. Kanisetti begins by condescendingly stating that Saṃskṛta being a language suited to programming is a silly claim that has been doing the rounds along with “pseudoscientific” achievements of ancient Indians such as flying machines and cloning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
