<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;whitney on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;whitney on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Sanskrit Grammar (Whitney)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/01_Sanskrit_Grammar_Whitney/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/01_Sanskrit_Grammar_Whitney/</guid>
      <description>SANSKRIT GRAMMAR
Including both the Classical Language, and
the older Dialects, of Veda and Brahmana
BY
WILLIAM DWIGHT WHITNEY
Late Professor of Sanskrit in Yale University, Knight of the Prussian Order
Pour le Mérite, Corresponding Member of the Académie des Inscrip-
tions et Belles-Lettres of the Institute of France, etc., Editor-
in-Chief of The Century Dictionary, an Encyclopedic
Lexicon of the English Language

CAMBRIDGE, MASSACHUSETTS
HARVARD UNIVERSITY PRESS
LONDON: GEOFFREY CUMBERLEGE</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Preface</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/02_Preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/02_Preface/</guid>
      <description>PREFACE TO THE FIRST EDITION.
It was in June, 1875, as I chanced to be for a day or two in Leipzig, that I was unexpectedly invited to prepare the Sanskrit grammar for the Indo-European series projected by Messrs. Breitkopf and Härtel. After some consideration, and consultation with friends, I accepted the task, and have since devoted to it what time could be spared from regular duties, after the satisfaction of engagements earlier formed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/03_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/03_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>INTRODUCTION. BRIEF ACCOUNT OF THE INDIAN LITERATURE.
It seems desirable to give here such a sketch of the history of Indian literature as shall show the relation to one another of the different periods and forms of the language treated in the following grammar, and the position of the works there quoted.
The name “Sanskrit” (saṁskṛta, 1087 d, adorned, elaborated, perfected), which is popularly applied to the whole ancient and sacred language of India, belongs more properly only to that dialect which, regulated and established by the labors of the native grammarians, has led for the last two thousand years or more an artificial life, like that of Latin during most of the same period in Europe, as the written and spoken means of communication of the learned and priestly caste; and which even at the present day fills that office.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Abbreviations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/04_Abbreviations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/04_Abbreviations/</guid>
      <description>ABBREVIATIONS.
AA. Āitareya-Āraṇyaka
AB. Āitareya-Brāhmaṇa.
AśS. Āśvalāyana-śrāuta-Sūtra.
AGS. Āśvalāyana-Gṛhya-Sūtra.
Āpast. Āpastamba-Sūtra.
APr. Atharva-Prātiśākhya.
AV. Atharva-Veda.
B. or Br. Brāhmaṇas.
BAU. Bṛhad-Āraṇyaka-Upaniṣad.
BhG. Bhagavad-Gītā.
BhP. Bhāgavata-Purāṇa.
BR. Böhtlingk and Roth (Petersburg Lexicon).
C. Classical Sanskrit.
ś. śakuntalā.
śatr. śatruṁjaya-Māhātmyam.
śB. śatapatha-Brāhmaṇa.
śśS. śān̄khāyana-śrāuta-Sūtra.
śGS. śān̄khāyana-Gṛhya-Sūtra.
ChU. Chāndogya-Upaniṣad.
śvU. śvetāśvatara-Upaniṣad.
DKC. Daśa-Kumāra-Carita.
E. Epos (MBh. and R.).
GB. Gopatha-Brāhmaṇa.
GGS. Gobhilīya-Gṛhya-Sūtra.
H. Hitopadeśa.
Har. Harivanśa.
JB. Jāiminīya (or Talavakāra) Brāhmaṇa.
JUB. Jāiminīya-Upaniṣad-Brāhmaṇa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Chapter I ALPHABET</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/05_Chapter_I_ALPHABET/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/05_Chapter_I_ALPHABET/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER I. ALPHABET.
1. The natives of India write their ancient and sacred language in a variety of alphabets — generally, in each part of the country, in the same alphabet which they use for their own vernacular. The mode of writing, however, which is employed throughout the heart of Aryan India, or in Hindustan proper, is alone adopted by European scholars: it is called the devanāgarī.
a. This name is of doubtful origin and value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Chapter II PRONUNCIATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/06_Chapter_II_PRONUNCIATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/06_Chapter_II_PRONUNCIATION/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER II. SYSTEM OF SOUNDS; PRONUNCIATION.
I. Vowels.
19. The a, i, and u-vowels. The Sanskrit has these three earliest and most universal vowels of Indo-European language, in both short and long form — अ a and आ ā, इ i and ई ī, उ u and ऊ ū. They are to be pronounced in the “Continental” or “Italian” manner — as in far or farther, pin and pique, pull and rule.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Chapter III EUPHONIC COMBINATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/07_Chapter_III_EUPHONIC_COMBINATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/07_Chapter_III_EUPHONIC_COMBINATION/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER III. RULES OF EUPHONIC COMBINATION.
Introductory.
98. The words in Sanskrit, as in the other languages related with it, are in great part analysable into roots, suffixes of derivation, and endings of inflection, these last being added mostly to stems containing suffixes, but also sometimes directly to roots.
a. There are, of course, a certain number of uninflected words—indeclinables, particles; and also not a few that are incapable of analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Chapter IV DECLENSION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/08_Chapter_IV_DECLENSION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/08_Chapter_IV_DECLENSION/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IV. DECLENSION.
261. The general subject of declension includes nouns, adjectives, and pronouns, all of which are inflected in essentially the same manner. But while the correspondence of nouns and adjectives is so close that they cannot well be separated in treatment (chap. V.), the pronouns, which exhibit many peculiarities, will be best dealt with in a separate chapter (VII.); and the words designating number, or numerals, also form a class peculiar enough to require to be presented by themselves (chap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Chapter V NOUNS AND ADJECTIVES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/09_Chapter_V_NOUNS_AND_ADJECTIVES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/09_Chapter_V_NOUNS_AND_ADJECTIVES/</guid>
      <description>NOUNS AND ADJECTIVES.
321. a. The accordance in inflection of substantive and adjective stems is so complete that the two cannot be separated in treatment from one another.
b. They may be classified, for convenience of description, as follows:
I. Stems in अ a;
II. Stems in इ i and उ u;
III. Stems in आ ā, ई ī, and ऊ ū: namely, A. radical-stems (and a few others inflected like them); B.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Chapter VI NUMERALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/10_Chapter_VI_NUMERALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/10_Chapter_VI_NUMERALS/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VI.  NUMERALS.
475. The simple cardinal numerals for the first ten numbers (which are the foundation of the whole class), with their derivatives, the tens, and with some of the higher members of the decimal series, are as follows:
1
एक
éka
10
दश
dáśa
100
शत
śatá
2
द्व
dvá
20
विंशति
viṅśatí
1000
सहस्र
sahásra
3
त्रि
trí
30
त्रिंशत्
triṅśát
10,000
अयुत
ayúta
4
चतुर्</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Chapter VII PRONOUNS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/11_Chapter_VII_PRONOUNS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/11_Chapter_VII_PRONOUNS/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VII. PRONOUNS.
490. The pronouns differ from the great mass of nouns and adjectives chiefly in that they come by derivation from another and a very limited set of roots, the so-called pronominal or demonstrative roots. But they have also many and marked peculiarities of inflection — some of which, however, find analogies in a few adjectives; and such adjectives will accordingly be described at the end of this chapter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Chapter VIII CONJUGATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/12_Chapter_VIII_CONJUGATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/12_Chapter_VIII_CONJUGATION/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VIII. CONJUGATION.
527. THE subject of conjugation or verbal inflection involves, as in the other languages of the family, the distinctions of voice, tense, mode, number, and person.
a. Further, besides the simpler or ordinary conjugation of a verbal root, there are certain more or less fully developed secondary or derivative conjugations.
528. Voice. There are (as in Greek) two voices, active and middle, distinguished by a difference in the personal endings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 Chapter IX PRESENT-SYSTEM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/13_Chapter_IX_PRESENT-SYSTEM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/13_Chapter_IX_PRESENT-SYSTEM/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IX. THE PRESENT-SYSTEM.
599. THE present-system, or system of forms coming from the present-stem, is composed (as was pointed out above) of a present indicative tense, together with a subjunctive (mostly lost in the classical language), an optative, an imperative, and a participle, and also a past tense, an augment-preterit, to which we give (by analogy with the Greek) the name of imperfect.
a. These forms often go in Sanskrit grammars by the name of &amp;ldquo;special tenses&amp;rdquo;, while the other tense-systems are styled &amp;ldquo;general tenses&amp;rdquo; — as if the former were made from a special tense-stem or modified root, while the latter came, all alike, from the root itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 Chapter X PERFECT-SYSTEM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/14_Chapter_X_PERFECT-SYSTEM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/14_Chapter_X_PERFECT-SYSTEM/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER X. THE PERFECT-SYSTEM.
780. THE perfect-system in the later language, as has been seen above (535), consists only of an indicative tense and a participle — both of them in the two voices, active and middle.
a. In the oldest language, the perfect has also its modes and its augment-preterit, or pluperfect, or is not less full in its apparatus of forms than is the present-system (see 808 ff.).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 Chapter XI AORIST SYSTEMS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/15_Chapter_XI_AORIST_SYSTEMS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/15_Chapter_XI_AORIST_SYSTEMS/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XI. THE AORIST SYSTEMS.
824. UNDER the name of aorist are included (as was pointed out above, 532) three quite distinct formations, each of which has its sub-varieties: namely —
I. A SIMPLE AORIST (equivalent to the Greek &amp;ldquo;second aorist&amp;rdquo;), analogous in all respects as to form and inflection with the imperfect. It has two varieties: 1. the root-aorist, with a tense-stem identical with the root (corresponding to an imperfect of the root-class); 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Chapter XII FUTURE-SYSTEMS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/16_Chapter_XII_FUTURE-SYSTEMS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/16_Chapter_XII_FUTURE-SYSTEMS/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XII. THE FUTURE-SYSTEMS.
931. THE verb has two futures, of very different age and character. The one has for tense-sign a sibilant followed by य ya, and is an inheritance from the time of Indo-European unity. The other is a periphrastic formation, made by appending an auxiliary verb to a derivative noun of agency, and it is a recent addition to the verb-system; its beginnings only are met with in the earliest language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 Chapter XIII VERBAL ADJECTIVES AND NOUNS: PARTICIPLES, INFINITIVES, GERUNDS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/17_Chapter_XIII_VERBAL_ADJECTIVES_AND_NOUNS_PARTICIPLES_INFINITIVES_GERUNDS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/17_Chapter_XIII_VERBAL_ADJECTIVES_AND_NOUNS_PARTICIPLES_INFINITIVES_GERUNDS/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIII. VERBAL ADJECTIVES AND NOUNS: PARTICIPLES, INFINITIVES, GERUNDS.
951 a. THOSE verbal adjectives, or participles, which are made from tense-stems, and so constitute a part of the various tense-systems, have been already treated. It remains to describe certain others, which, being made directly from the root itself, belong to the verbal system as a whole, and not to any particular part of it.
b. The infinitive (with a few sporadic exceptions in the older language) also comes in all cases from the root directly, and not from any of the derived tense-stems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 Chapter XIV DERIVATIVE OR SECONDARY CONJUGATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/18_Chapter_XIV_DERIVATIVE_OR_SECONDARY_CONJUGATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/18_Chapter_XIV_DERIVATIVE_OR_SECONDARY_CONJUGATION/</guid>
      <description>996. SECONDARY conjugations are those in which a whole system of forms, like that already described as made from the simple root, is made, with greater or less completeness, from a derivative conjugation-stem; and is also usually connected with a certain definite modification of the original radical sense.
a. We have seen, indeed, that the tense-systems are also for the most part made from derivative-stems; and even that, in some cases, such stems assume the appearance and value of roots, and are made the basis of a complete conjugational system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 Chapter XV PERIPHRASTIC AND COMPOUND CONJUGATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/19_Chapter_XV_PERIPHRASTIC_AND_COMPOUND_CONJUGATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/19_Chapter_XV_PERIPHRASTIC_AND_COMPOUND_CONJUGATION/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XV. PERIPHRASTIC AND COMPOUND CONJUGATION.
1069. ONE periphrastic formation, the periphrastic future, has been already described (942 ff.), since it has become in the later language a recognized part of every verbal conjugation, and since, though still remaining essentially periphrastic, it has been so fused in its parts and altered in construction as to assume in considerable measure the semblance of an integral tense-formation.
By far the most important other formation of the class is —</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Chapter XVI INDECLINABLES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/20_Chapter_XVI_INDECLINABLES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/20_Chapter_XVI_INDECLINABLES/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVI. INDECLINABLES.
1096. THE indeclinable words are less distinctly divided into separate parts of speech in Sanskrit than is usual elsewhere in Indo-European language — especially owing to the fact that the class of prepositions hardly has a real existence, but is represented by certain adverbial words which are to a greater or less extent used prepositionally. They will, however, be briefly described here under the usual heads.
Adverbs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Chapter XVII DERIVATION OF DECLINABLE STEMS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/21_Chapter_XVII_DERIVATION_OF_DECLINABLE_STEMS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/21_Chapter_XVII_DERIVATION_OF_DECLINABLE_STEMS/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVII. DERIVATION OF DECLINABLE STEMS.
1136. THE formation from roots of conjugable stems — namely, tense-stems, mode-stems, and stems of secondary conjugation (not essentially different from one another, nor, it is believed, ultimately from the formation of declined stems) — was most conveniently treated above, in the chapters devoted to the verb. Likewise the formation of adverbs by derivation (not essentially different from case-formation), in the chapter devoted to particles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 Chapter XVIII FORMATION OF COMPOUND STEMS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/22_Chapter_XVIII_FORMATION_OF_COMPOUND_STEMS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/22_Chapter_XVIII_FORMATION_OF_COMPOUND_STEMS/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVIII. FORMATION OF COMPOUND STEMS.
1246. THE frequent combination of declinable stems with one another to form compounds which then are treated as if simple, in respect to accent, inflection, and construction, is a conspicuous feature of the language, from its earliest period.
a. There is, however, a marked difference between the earlier and the later language as regards the length and intricacy of the combinations allowed. In Veda and Brāhmaṇa, it is quite rare that more than two stems are compounded together — except that to some much used and familiar compound, as to an integral word, a further element is sometimes added.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 Appendix</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/23_Appendix/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/23_Appendix/</guid>
      <description>APPENDIX.
A. The following text is given (as proposed above, 3) in order to illustrate by an example the variety of Sanskrit type in use. It is given twice over, and a transliteration into European letters follows. The text is a fable extracted from the first book of the Hitopadeśa.
The Hunter, Deer, Boar, and Jackal.


āsīt kalyāṇakaṭakavāstavyo bhāiravo nāma vyādhaḥ. sa cāi ’kadā māṅsalubdhaḥ san dhanur ādāya vindhyāṭavīmadhyaṁ gataḥ.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 Sanskrit Index</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/24_Sanskrit_Index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/24_Sanskrit_Index/</guid>
      <description>SANSKRIT INDEX.
The references in both Indexes are to paragraphs. In this one, many abbreviations are used; but it is believed that they will be found self-explaining. For example, &amp;ldquo;pron.&amp;rdquo; is pronunciation; &amp;ldquo;euph.&amp;rdquo; points out anything relating to phonetic form or euphonic combination; &amp;ldquo;pres.&amp;rdquo;, to present-system; &amp;ldquo;int.&amp;rdquo; is intensive; &amp;ldquo;des.&amp;rdquo; is desiderative; and so on. A prefixed hyphen denotes a suffix; one appended, a prefix.
a, pron. etc., 19–22, combination with following vowel, 126, 127; loss of initial after e and o, 135, 175 a; resulting accent, 135 a; not liable to guṇa, 235 a; lightened to i or u, 249; lost in weakened syllable, 253.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 General Index</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/25_General_Index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/25_General_Index/</guid>
      <description>GENERAL INDEX.
a-aorist (simple aorist, 2), 824, 846–54: in the later language, 846; roots forming it in the older language, 847; inflection, 848; modes, 849–51; participles, 852; irregularities, 853, 854.
a-class (first, bhū-class) of verbs, 606, 734–50; formation of stem, 734; inflection, 735–43; roots of the class, 744; irregularities, 745–50.
á-class or accented a-class (sixth, tud-class) of verbs, 606, 751–8: formation of stem, 751; inflection, 752; roots of the class, 753, 754; irregularities, 755–8.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 Errata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/26_Errata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/whitney/26_Errata/</guid>
      <description>ERRATA.
A few entirely obvious misprints are passed without notice.
p. 5,
10 c,
last l.
—
for क
read
की
42,
125 b,
l. 3
—
for (for prayuga)
&amp;quot;
(for prayuga?).
67,
199 c,
l. 3
—
for IB.
&amp;quot;
JB.
92,
276 a,
l. 2
—
for ledgues
&amp;quot;
leagues.
94,
281 b,
l. 4
—
read ‘kṣahṛdayaṁ dātā rājā ’śvahṛ-.
99,
296 b,
l. 10
—</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
