<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;लक्ष्मणः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/niruktam/laxmaNaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;लक्ष्मणः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/niruktam/laxmaNaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/niruktam/laxmaNaH/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/niruktam/laxmaNaH/notes/</guid>
      <description>EXEGETICAL AND CKITICAL NOTES CHAPTER I
 1.] Muir translates the passage as follows : A sacred record (samamnaya) has been compiled, which is to be expounded. This is called the Nighantus.&amp;rsquo; 1 His rendering of samamnaya by&amp;rsquo; a sacred record * is not quite correct. &amp;lsquo;It may be that he has been led to this conclusion on account of misunderstanding the following explanatory note of Durgacarya :&amp;rsquo; The meaning is, that this compila tion has been put together by seers, as being an illustration for understanding the meaning of the Vedic stanzas, in a single list, divided into five chapters/ He explains the word samamnaya as follows :&amp;rsquo; The list of words beginning with gaus and ending with devapatnl is called samamnaya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Translation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/niruktam/laxmaNaH/translation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/niruktam/laxmaNaH/translation/</guid>
      <description>THE NIRUKTA
  CHAPTER I
A TRADITIONAL list (of words) has been handed down (to us). It is to be (here) explained. This same list is called Ni-ghantavas.1
From what (root) is (the word) Ni-ghantavas derived? They are words quoted fromthe Vedas (ni-gamaih)? Having been repeatedly gathered together3 fromVedic hymns, they have been handed down by tradition. Aupamanyava holds that, as these are the quoted words of the Vedas, they are called Ni ghantavas on account of their being quoted (t/ii-gamanaat).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
