<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Sanskrit Phobia on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Sanskrit Phobia on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Caste system</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Caste_system/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Caste_system/</guid>
      <description>Also see: Restricted social role.
Caste system reinforcement  Claim: &amp;ldquo;Sanskrit literature reinforces the hindu caste system.&amp;rdquo;
 Why single out Sanskrit epics for this analysis? What about Hindi, Tamil, Kannada, Telugu epics that also reinforce that system? And some counter-religious bauddha and jaina texts? All ancient scholarship (irrespective of language and country), was to a huge degree, elite scholarship.
Why would you turn a blind eye to mountains of Sanskrit works (hindu, buddhist, jain) which talk nothing about caste or gender roles in a way you dislike?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Content-scope</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/content-scope/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/content-scope/</guid>
      <description>Examples of wide scope Post-1947 Popular and award-winning novels encompassing history (Eg. Bhairappa&amp;rsquo;s sArtha) and science fiction (bhuvanam AnIta) have been published.
Pre-1947  James R. Ballantyne wrote Iṅglaṇḍīya-bhāṣā-vyākaraṇam  The Pandit (काशीविद्यासुधानिधिः), a Monthly Journal (1866 to 1920), of the Benares College, devoted to Sanskrit Literature carried the following:
 translations into Sanskrit of John Locke’s An Essay Concerning Human Understanding Bishop Berkeley’s A Treatise Concerning the Principles of Human Knowledge Vitthala Shastri&amp;rsquo;s Sanskrit commentary on Francis Bacon’s Novum Organum  Misconception examples  In post-colonial India, no single Brahmin has written any meaningful modern book in Sanskrit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dead language</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Dead_language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Dead_language/</guid>
      <description>Some limited decline  Q15.  Lay use  Despite contrary socio-economic forces, it is vitally alive. For numbers, seethis thread. Just search Youtube for Sanskrit videos - even omitting ancient hymns, you will find a lot. &amp;ldquo;Sanskrit villages&amp;rdquo; -  mattUru 1.   Interesting account of sanskrit use from the perspective of western academics, with references: NLL.  Thriving literary scene and scholarship  200-300 Mahakavyas composed in Sanskrit since independence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hard language</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Hard_language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Hard_language/</guid>
      <description>Not so - the &amp;ldquo;grammar translation method&amp;rdquo; introduced and imposed by the British, and exposure to only hard registers of sanskrit causes this wrong impression. See this detailed speech. With an immersive approach, conversational Sanskrit is as easy as any other language. Of course, advanced/ masterful usage requires serveral years of dedicated effort - like in any other language. [Funny &amp;ldquo;Hitler learns Sanskrit&amp;rdquo; video.] If the right register (Simple Standard Sanskrit - archive) is used, sanskrit is quite easy for all Indians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impractical to switch</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Impractical_to_switch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Impractical_to_switch/</guid>
      <description> It is impractical to switch to using sanskrit as the link language of India.  Hebrew example: WP15.    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern tech terms</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Modern_tech_terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Modern_tech_terms/</guid>
      <description>Accusation: You cannot do or teach modern technical subjects (eg. maths, physics, chemistry, biology&amp;hellip;) in sanskrit. False - You can, and it will be quite precise, meaningful and fun. Example of a brief description of titration and stellar chain reactions - MT16(TW16). Chinese, Japanese, Israelis and Germans do science in their own languages. Among them, Hebrew is a revived language. That said, we can still concede that we can expediently use English for such subjects while retaining sanskrit for the soft sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Money</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Money/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Money/</guid>
      <description>Sanskrit is not the optimal language to learn in order to earn more money. So, we should ditch it and teach German, Chinese, etc.. [FP]  Earning more money is not the only reason to teach languages to our children. There are very strong humanistic and aesthetic reasons to favor Sanskrit. If we want diversity in the international languages taught to our children, that is welcome - let them compete with English - not Sanskrit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restricted social role</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Restricted_social_role/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Restricted_social_role/</guid>
      <description>In the past - see note on &amp;ldquo;history&amp;rdquo; above, which indicates clear usage outside ritual.  Misconception  Accusation: Sanskrit is the language of Brahmins, and that too male brahmins. Further, it was only used for shAstra-s and kAvya-s.  shUdra-usage   There are plenty of Sanskrit scholars (right from upaniShadic seers such as Aitreya mahidAsa to dArA-shikoh / Abdul Rahim Khan) who were not brahmaNa-s or kShatriya-s. Eg: mAtanga-divAkara the chaNDAla [TW].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanskrit suppresses other (Indian) languages</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Sanskrit_suppresses_other_Indian_languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/misconceptions/Sanskrit_Phobia/Sanskrit_suppresses_other_Indian_languages/</guid>
      <description>Some languages have an oppressor - oppressed relationship. Eg: Arabic vs Egyptian. English vs Iniut. Though Sanskrit was a link language across Asia,this was not the case with Sanskrit and other languages. Rather, their relationship was of the nourisher-nourished type. References: Balram Shukla&amp;rsquo;s answer here.  Enrichment of other languages  Sanskrit enriched local languages - with its special ability to coin new words.  A grateful acknowledgement of influence on Thai - YTTh2015.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
