<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;शिक्षा on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;शिक्षा on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Labial oṣṭhya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/labial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/labial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;v-labial-or-dento-labial&#34;&gt;v: labial or dento-labial&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;phonetic-drift&#34;&gt;Phonetic drift&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It could have been a bi-labial ; but we have no positive proof to that effect. &amp;hellip;. Siddheshwar  Varma ( 1929), p. 129, says: &amp;quot; For at least a thousand years before  Brugmann, Indian grammarians had observed, and correctly, that the  Sanskrit v in the medial and final positions was not a labio-dental.&amp;quot; The  Dantyoṣṭhyavidhi , p. 4, provides lists of variation between pure labial and  labio-dental varieties of v and b in the Atharvaveda . It may be argued  that the euphonic alternation of v with the pure labial u, and its dialectal  and historical relationship with the pure labial b in Sanskrit suggest its  predominant feature of labiality. It is possible that gradually the dental articulator entered the pronunciation of v to keep it distinct from b which  is bi-labial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>अनुनासिकम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/anunAsikam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/anunAsikam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;परदशकचचरणन&#34;&gt;प्रादेशिकोच्चारणानि&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;रङ्गचिह्नं लिखितेऽलिखितेऽपि वा, अनुनासिकस्य व्याहरणं कथं वा कर्तव्यम् इति मुख्यः प्रश्नोऽत्र वर्तते । अस्यास्य देशभेदेन विभिद्यते समभिन्याहरणम् । &amp;lsquo;गँ, गुँ, ग्वं, ग्वँ,&amp;rsquo; इत्येवम् आदीनि क्रियन्तेऽस्योदीरणानि । एतान्य् असमीचीनान्य् एवेति प्रतिभाति, यतस् तत्र गकारस्य कण्ठ्यस्य, उकार-वकारयोर् ओष्ठ्य-योग-दने नास्ति प्रमाण-लेशोऽपि । अनुस्वारस्य नासिकैव स्थानम् , अनुनासिकस्य तु मुखनासिके । एवं सति स्थानान्तरयोः कण्ठ्यौष्ठयोवर्णयोर् भाषणं नैव कथंचिद् अपि प्रमाणयितुं शक्यते । व्याहरण-शुद्धाशुद्धत्व-विनिर्णये स्थानविचार एव बलवत्तरं प्रमाणं भवति ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;सात्वळेकरश्रीपदः सामवेदसंहिताभूमिकायाम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;पणनय-शकष-मतम&#34;&gt;पाणिनीय-शिक्षा-मतम्&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अनुनासिकोच्चारण-विषये यद् उक्तं पाणिनीयायां शिक्षायां तत् तु तत्वतो ऽनुसन्धेयम् अत्र । … एवं सति, तस्य रङ्गस्य &amp;lsquo;ग्वँ, ग्वं, गुं, &amp;rsquo; इत्यादीनि मार्दवहीनानि कठोराणि स्थानव्यभिचार-दोष-दुष्टानि व्याहरणानि, सर्वथा त्याज्यान्य् एवेति । एवं शषसहरेफेषु परेषु सत्सु अनुनासिक-पूर्वं स्वरं दीर्घम् उच्चार्य नासिकायाम् एवानुनासिक गुञ्जयित्वा, तदूर्ध्वम् अग्रेवासिनं वर्णं प्रयुञ्जीयात्, यथा &amp;rsquo; वसते&amp;rsquo; इत्यस्य &amp;rsquo; वा अंसते &amp;rsquo; इति । न तु &amp;lsquo;वग्वँसते&amp;rsquo; इति ।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>उच्चारण-परिवर्तनम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/uchchAraNa-parivartanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/uchchAraNa-parivartanam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;परवरतनकरम&#34;&gt;परिवर्तनक्रमः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../images/phonetic_transformation.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/phonetic_transformation.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;{ }&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../images/phonetic_transformation_text.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/phonetic_transformation_text.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;{ }&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The orthodox Indian tradition has greatly respected the relationship of a teacher and his disciple and has continued to believe that nothing ever changed in this oral transmission. It is believed that the oral text has been handed down from one generation to the next without any changes. However, we must view a preliterate oral tradition with a fresh linguistic and analytical approach. We must distinguish a “pseudo-connection” from a “real connection” between two successive synchronic states of a preliterate oral text.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Within the veda-s, one finds great inconsistency in applicaiton of phonetic rules (&amp;ldquo;प्र णो &amp;quot; इत्यपि दृश्यते, &amp;ldquo;प्र नो&amp;rdquo; इत्यपि।) - so that &amp;ldquo;the preredaction oral traditions were extremely irregular, imperfect, flexible and, therefore, ironically, more “natural” to ancient oral literature, and that a major amount of the phonetic “information” which we find in the existing Vedic recensions can hardly be considered to represent the original compositions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;परदशक-परवरतनन&#34;&gt;प्रादेशिक-परिवर्तनानि&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;वर्ण-व्यत्ययो ऽन्यत्र द्रष्टव्यः।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ए ओ ऐ औ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/e-o-ai-au/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/e-o-ai-au/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;सन्ध्यक्षर+उच्चारणम्॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;परचन-सथत&#34;&gt;प्राचीना स्थितिः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पुरा - &amp;ldquo;एओ=अइ=अय्/ अउ=अw, ऐऔ → आइ=आय्/ आउ=आw&amp;rdquo;) इति।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Paṇini-shixA has also asked to pronounce it ai, &amp;ldquo;अर्धमात्रा तु कण्ठस्य एकार+ओकारयोर्भवेत् &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Any sonorant consonant can comprise the second part of a complex syllable nucleus; all can form diphthongs with any of the vowels *e, *o, *ē, *ō (such as *ey, *oy, *ēy, *ōy, *ew, *ow, *em, *en, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Proto-Indo-European phonology wiki article&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;परसपर-ववक&#34;&gt;परस्पर-विवेकः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;आर्यभाषासु, यथा मम ग्रामभाषायां ba[y] (स एव), bā[y] (महिला) इत्यादयो बहवः शब्दाः सन्ति यत्र a[y]-ā[y] भेदेन a[w]-ā[w] भेदेन चार्थभेदोऽपि भवति। - उज्ज्वलः।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>तालु</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/tAluH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/tAluH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;सर&#34;&gt;सारः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;तालु-मूर्धयोस् स्थाने विवादः - दन्तमूर्धयोर् मध्ये ताल्व् इति केचित्, दन्त-ताल्वोर् मध्ये मूर्धेत्य् अपरे (श्रीरमणशर्मणः शिक्षाप्रथमक्लृप्तौ)। परपक्ष उत्तरो भाति।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;सम्पदानन्दमिश्रो &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pvaal2/status/1226186031579516930&#34;&gt;ऽत्र&lt;/a&gt; ।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;thumbnail&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../images/kaNTha-tAlu-mUrdhA-1.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/kaNTha-tAlu-mUrdhA-1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;    &lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;        कण्ठ-तालु-मूर्धाः १&#xA;        &#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;thumbnail&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../images/kaNTha-tAlu-mUrdhA-2.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/kaNTha-tAlu-mUrdhA-2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;    &lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;        कण्ठ-तालु-मूर्धाः २&#xA;        &#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;दनतमल-पषठ-सथनम&#34;&gt;दन्तमूल-पृष्ठे स्थानम्&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;च and ज are pronounced  by raising the blade, or front, of the tongue toward or against the hard palate just behind the alveolar ridge (the gums).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;दष&#34;&gt;दोषः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;प्रायेण विद्वांसोऽपि ञकारं न वदन्ति &amp;ldquo;पञ्च, पञ्चतन्त्रम्, पञ्जाब्&amp;rdquo; इत्यादिषु शब्देषु - नकार एव श्रूयते। &lt;a href=&#34;https://voca.ro/17TqgNMlyF8j&#34;&gt;https://voca.ro/17TqgNMlyF8j&lt;/a&gt; इति श्रुणुध्वम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This articulation leads to the inability to produce sufficiently distinct sounds when saying पञ्च vs पन्च . Hence, it is wrong - the contact with the hard palate should be further back.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;यकारशकार-जिह्वास्पर्श-स्थानम् एकात्र, भवदभिमत-चवर्गस्थानम् अन्यत्रेत्य् उच्चारणप्रयोगसिद्धम् अशास्त्रीयम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;मरध-पषठ-सथनम&#34;&gt;मूर्ध-पृष्ठे स्थानम्&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;जिह्वामध्यस्य तालुनि स्वर्शो भवति।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;यकरद-ञकरसय-भद&#34;&gt;यँकाराद् ञकारस्य भेदः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;यँकारसाम्यविषये चिन्तयेम। तत्र स्थानं तालुर् नासिका च। आभ्यन्तरप्रयत्नश्च  + ईषत्स्पृष्ट इति। बाह्यप्रयत्नः - संवारो नादो घोषश्च, अल्पप्राणस् तथा।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ञकारम् ईक्षताम्। तत्र स्थानं तालुर् नासिका च। आभ्यन्तरप्रयत्नश्च स्पृष्ट इति। बाह्यप्रयत्नः - संवारो नादो घोषश्च, अल्पप्राणस् तथा।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;लँनयोर् यो भेदः, यावान् चासौ, यँञयोर् अपि स एव, तावान् एव।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>दन्त्याः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/dantyAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/dantyAH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;दनतयतवम&#34;&gt;दन्त्यत्वम्&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;शौनकीय-चतुरध्यायिकायाम् -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;१.१.२४. दन्त्यानां जिह्वाग्रं प्रस्तीर्णम् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whitney (1.24). G: 1.1.24. Most mss. read jivhāgram.&#xA;Translation: For dental sounds, the tip of the tongue spread flat [is the articulator].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पाणिनीये ऽपि -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider, for instance, the rule P.7.3.73 (लुग्वा दुहदिहलिहगुहामात्मनेपदे दन्त्ये). The rule says that after the listed roots, the affix -ksa- of the aorist is optionally (or preferably, if one accepts Kiparsky’s interpretation of vā) deleted before a middle termination beginning in a dantya sound. The affixes -dhvam and -ta are undoubtedly dantya-initial affixes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>मात्रा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/mAtrA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/mAtrA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;सपसटकरण-यतन&#34;&gt;स्पस्टीकरणे यत्नः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;नम्बूतिरिषु विरामस्थानेषु (ऋगर्धे यथा) मात्रा ऽनुवचनेन स्पष्टीक्रियते। यथा -&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ह्रस्वे - देव - देव,अ&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;दीर्घे - पृथिवी - पृथिवी,ई,ई&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;प्लुते - ये३ यजामहे - ये,ए,ए,ए यजामहे,ए,ए&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>मूर्धा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/mUrdhA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/mUrdhA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;retroflex-पकष&#34;&gt;Retroflex-पक्षः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;जिह्वाया अधोभागसंस्पर्शेन मूर्धन्यवर्णा जन्यन्त, ऊर्ध्वभागसंस्पर्शेन तालव्यादिवर्णा इति निश्चयेनालम् मन्ये।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;णकारस् तु मूर्धां विना दुष्कर उच्चरितुम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;the dental, palatal, and retroflex sounds show a clear&#xA;hierarchy. dental &amp;lt; palatal &amp;lt; retroflex&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Panini’s rule 8.4.40 ( स्तोः श्चुनाश्चुः) says that a dental stop or sibilant is replaced by the corresponding palatal stop or sibilant if followed or preceded by a palatal stop or sibilant, e.g., तच्च .&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A palatal never becomes a dental. Panini’s rule 8.4.41 (ष्टुना ष्टुः ) says that a dental stop or sibilant is replaced by the corresponding retroflex stop or sibilant if followed or preceded by a retroflex stop or sibilant, e.g., रामष्टीकाम्. A retroflex consonant never becomes dental.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Similarly, there are rules to change palatals into retroflex consonants, e.g., राज् + भिस् = राड्भिः, but no retroflex consonant is ever changed into a palatal. This gives us a hierarchy of dental →palatal → retroflex, such that there are no changes in the reverse direction. &amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;इतहस&#34;&gt;इतिहासः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;अभपरय&#34;&gt;अभिप्रायाः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;द्राविडप्रायभाषान्तरभाषकैर् वेदरक्षकैः शनैर् वेदेष्वपि मूर्धन्यवर्णा भाविता इति माधवादयः केचित्। ततः प्रागित्यन्ये  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1176332528795443203&#34;&gt;केचित्&lt;/a&gt;।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;माधवो &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/1306422/Genesis_of_Rgvedic_retroflexion_a_historical_and_sociolinguistic_investigation&#34;&gt;ऽत्र&lt;/a&gt;।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;उच्चारणपरिवर्तने &lt;a href=&#34;../uchchAraNa-parivartanam/&#34;&gt;ऽत्र&lt;/a&gt; दृश्यताम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;alveolar-कल&#34;&gt;Alveolar-कालः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Classical Greek: It is not Delta or Tau with retroflexes - they&amp;rsquo;re alveolar. And, θ is mahAprANa (aspirated). W Eur pronunciation of T, D is NOT retroflex (tongue curl), as per this &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_alphabet&#34;&gt;wiki key&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Western European pronunciation of T, D is NOT retroflex (tongue curl). There is no separate retroflex Na. See examples in &lt;a href=&#34;../uchchAraNa-parivartanam/&#34;&gt;language drift page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Avestan and reconstructed proto-Indo-Iranic has post-alveolar or palatal श्/š. It does not have a separate retroflex टवर्ग - just dental (and possibly alveolar in case of PII).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ब्राह्मीलिप्यां दन्त्यवर्णचिह्नानि मूर्धन्यवर्णचिह्नानि समानमूलानि।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I think ancient Dravidian had alveolar ṯ, in addition to dental t and retroflex ṭ. Similarly it likely had retroflex, alveolar and dental n.  Malayalam has all these.  In Dravidian, there is a tendency for combinations such as l+ dental t to become alveolar ṯ. &amp;hellip; Vilkkŭ means to sell. The root is &amp;ldquo;vil&amp;rdquo;. Past tense ‘sold’, is formed by vil+tu and it becomes viṯṯu (alveolar ṯ). Ēlkkŭ = to take responsibility, to get hit, etc.  Past tense ēl+tu = ēṯṯu (alveolar ṯ).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;retroflex-समभत&#34;&gt;Retroflex-सम्भूतिः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;णत्वषत्वयोर् अर्वाचीनता&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;णत्वं षत्वं चापवादभूयिष्ठम् भाषायाम् - पाणिनीयसूत्राणि तत्र प्रमाणम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;वेदेष्वपि - &amp;ldquo;प्र णो &amp;quot; इत्यपि दृश्यते, &amp;ldquo;प्र नो&amp;rdquo; इत्यपि।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;एवञ्च महाभाष्ये १.१.५६ इत्यत्र - &amp;ldquo;एवं हि श्रूयते- यर्वाणस्तर्वाणो नाम ऋषयो बभूवुः प्रत्यक्षधर्माणः परापरज्ञा विदितवेदितव्या अधिगतयाथातथ्याः। ते तत्रभवन्तो &amp;ldquo;यद्वा नस्, तद्वा न&amp;rdquo; इति प्रयोक्तव्ये &amp;ldquo;यर्वाणस् तर्वाण&amp;rdquo; इति प्रयुञ्ञ्जते, याज्ञे पुनः कर्मणि नापभाषन्ते।&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fortunatov’s Law: &amp;ldquo;IE l + dental = l is dropped and the dental is changed to a cerebral&amp;rdquo;.  (cf. Sk पट- ‘cloth’, O Slav. platino , Russ, polotno; sk भाषा , Lithuanian balsa - ‘voice’)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Just as alveolar t and d are rendered retroflex in Indian English, so must bilingual speakers of Sanskrit and some retroflexed language have introduced retroflex into sanskrit.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In later southern texts and tradition, we find la being replaced with La (mangaLa).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This further suggests that a feature like retroflexion, not genetically evolved, is a product the process of phonetic approximation (cf. Lovins:240) of the phonic material of a given nonretroflexed language by the speakers of a retroflexed langrage.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;षकरदभव&#34;&gt;षकारोद्भवः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The ruki rule says that the Indo-European *s is changed to श् in Indo Iranian if preceded by r, u k, or i. This particular rule ceases to be productive in Indo-Aryan except as a derivation of retroflex ष्. Panini&amp;rsquo;s rules 8.3.57 and 8.3.59 (इण्कोः, आदेशप्रत्यययोः) say that स् which is either a substitute or a part of an affix is replaced by ष्, if preceeded by इण्, कुँ. (देवे + सु - देवेषु)&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;However, if we look at the present text of the Rgveda, we find changes like the ones mentioned above taking place even when the conditioning sound belongs to a different word. All that seems to matter is the sound sequence within a metrical foot (pada). A metrical foot is looked upon as if it is a continuous sequence, and the awareness of word boundaries is dispensed with in making changes like n&amp;gt;n and s&amp;gt;s.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;ष् is not present in northern Dravidian languages and is absent from Old Kannada, Old Telugu and Old Tamil. &amp;hellip; the development of ष् in Sanskrit, by a special modification of the ruki rule, was a somewhat different process from the emergence of ट ठ ड ढ ण. However, later phonemicization of ष् is indirectly connected with the general levelling of all retroflex sounds.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Now ष् is a cerebral by convention only. It is, like र् a cerebralizer, rather than a cerebral, has been differentiated from the palatal श्, its fellow hush-sound, party for graphical and partly for phonetic reasons. So we find अष्टौ, but अशीतिः, पृष्ट and प्रश्न.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This phoneme is not carried into Middle Indian and for षष्, we find छ, which seems to show that ष् is a graphic variant of क्ष्, regular predecessor of छ् or ख् in Middle Indian. The later confusion of ष् and ख्, both phonetically and graphically (the Gujarati अक्षर for ख् is a form of नागरी ष्.)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;श्र् to ष् reduction: In prakrits - श्रयते → षयति, श्मश्रु → मषु, श्रमण → षमन&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This “phonological retroflexion” may be viewed in a functional sense in that all three sounds ऋ, र्, and ष् are “cerebralizers,” if not all cerebrals themselves in the view of the Pratisakhyas. In later texts such as the Paniniya-SiksA, both ऋ and र्, along with ष् are classified as retroflexes, and thus all of them become “cerebralizers” and cerebrals.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This “development” may be viewed as a phonetic development, but at the same time one may speculate that the phonological behavior of these sounds—their phonological or functional retroflexion- may have at least partially contributed to this phonetic shift. Thus, we find that the phonological requirements in Paninian grammar are greatly facilitated if we assume that r and r had the same point-of-articulation classification (Bare 1976:171).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;मरधनयसवकर&#34;&gt;मूर्धन्यस्वीकारः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Aitareya Āraṇyaka already records a debate on whether the Saṃhitā of the R̥gveda is अणकार and अषकार, or सणकार and सषकार, and concludes that the tradition represented by the author of this Āraṇyaka follows the lineage of Māṇḍūkeya, and that the Saṃhitā should be recited सणकार and सषकार.  But the discussion attests to the historical fact that some reciters were in favor of an अणकार and अषकार recitation of the R̥gveda.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>वकारः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/vakAraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/vakAraH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ओष्ठः स्थानम्, दन्ताः करणम् इति केचित्। दन्तोष्ठौ स्थानम् इत्य् अपरे।  वकारस्योत्पत्तिर् दन्तौष्ठाभ्याम् एवेति सर्वैः प्रतिपन्नम्। देशपाण्डेय-माधव-प्रबन्धो दृश्यः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The aim of this paper is not to prove that for Pānini v did not involve teeth in any capacity or that it was a pure bi-labial sound. It could have been a bi-labial ; but we have no positive proof to that effect.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;M Deshpande&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>विसर्गः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/visargaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/visargaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;सथनम&#34;&gt;स्थानम्&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;कणठरस&#34;&gt;कण्ठोरसी&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ऋक्प्रातिशाख्ये तैत्तिरीयप्रातिशाख्ये (कण्ठस्थानौ हकारविसर्जनीयौ॥२.४६॥) वाजसनेयिप्रातिशाख्ये च विसर्जनीयः &lt;strong&gt;कण्ठ्य&lt;/strong&gt; इत्युक्तः।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;किन्तु ऋक्प्रातिशाख्ये कथ्यते यत्, केचिदाचार्या इमम् &lt;strong&gt;उरस्यं&lt;/strong&gt; मन्वते इति - केचिदेता उरस्यौ। (ऋ०प्रा० १। ४०)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अत्र हकार-विसर्जनीययोर् भेद एव विवक्षितो भाति,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;स च प्रयत्न-विभागय् उच्यते।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नूनं विसर्गोचितो वायुरोधो मुख-विवरे हककारादिवत् कण्ठैकदेशे हि भवतीति नानुभूयते (यद्य् अपि तद् अपि स्थानं न तिरस्-क्रियते)।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अत एव च विसर्गस्य संहितायां स्थान्तरप्राप्तिश् च प्रसज्यतेतमाम् - शर्-उपध्मानीयादेशैः।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;परव-सवर-सथन-कवचत&#34;&gt;पूर्व-स्वर-स्थानं क्वचित्&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तत्रैव तैत्तिरीयप्रातिशाख्यानुसारं विसर्जनीयस्य स्थानान्तरम् अप्युक्तम् -&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यस्मात् स्वरात् परं विसर्जनीयस्तिष्ठति तस्येव उच्चारण-स्थानं भवति विसर्जनीयस्य (पूर्वान्तसस्थानो विसर्जनीयः॥२.४८॥)।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>हकारोत्तरानुनासिकाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/hakArottAnunAsikAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/hakArottAnunAsikAH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;उचचरणभद&#34;&gt;उच्चारणभेदः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;केचन ब्राह्मण, वह्नि…, ग्रुह्णमि इत्यादीनां वचने हकारानुनासिकयोः क्रमम् परिवर्तयन्ति।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;पणनयकल&#34;&gt;पाणिनीयकाले&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;sUtras such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://ashtadhyayi.github.io/suutra/8.3/8.3.26/&#34;&gt;https://ashtadhyayi.github.io/suutra/8.3/8.3.26/&lt;/a&gt; (he mapare maḥ, napare naḥ) provides evidence that at the time of pANini, the sequence hm and hn was clearly prevalent in spoken language.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As best as I know, historically all these clusters are h-initial clusters.  The reasons are not hard to see.  Just as -jñ- in forms like rājñaḥ is a contraction of -jan- in rājan, similarly -hn- in ahnaḥ is a contraction of -han- in ahan.  - MD&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ह्रस्व-ऎ-ऒ-कारौ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/hrasva-e-o/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/hrasva-e-o/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;दवनगरय-चहनन&#34;&gt;देवनागर्यां चिह्नानि&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ऎ ऒ ए᳘ ओ᳘&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ससकत-परयग&#34;&gt;संस्कृते प्रयोगः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सूचनास्रोतांसि -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.unicode.org/L2/L2011/11007-length-mark-candra-below.pdf&#34;&gt;श्रीरमणशर्मलेखात्&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;लक-ऽभव&#34;&gt;लोके ऽभावः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Patañjali goes on to note that such pronunciation is not found&#xA;anywhere else either in common (i.e. non-Vedic) Sanskrit or Vedic Sanskrit:&#xA;नैव हि लोके नाप्यन्यस्मिन् वेदे अर्ध एकारः अर्ध ओकारो वा अस्ति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;समवद&#34;&gt;सामवेदे&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Patañjali, the traditional authority on Paninian grammar, says in his Mahābhāṣya while commenting on the 3rd Śiva Sūtra ē ōṅ  एओङ् (and once more later while commenting on ēca igghrasvādēśē, Pāṇini 1/1/48):&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
