<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०० on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०० on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१ EDITORIAL FOREWORD BALASUBRAHMANYAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/1_EDITORIAL_FOREWORD_BALASUBRAHMANYAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/1_EDITORIAL_FOREWORD_BALASUBRAHMANYAM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. It is a well-known fact that Panini(P.), the doyen among descriptive linguists in Ancient India, devoted 380 rules to a systematic study of accentuation of the sacred language (Chandas) and Bhāṣā in the Aṣṭādhyayi (=A.). Although Katyayana and Patanjali attempted to interpret P.&amp;rsquo;s accentual calculus, later investigators have simply assigned a marginal niche to P.&amp;rsquo;s system of accentuation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. The Paninian approach was embodied in a number of subsequent manuals on accentuation such as svarasiromani, svaraprakriya, svarakaumudi, svaramanjari and the svarasiddhantacandrikā (=SSC).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२ PREFACE SIVARAMAKRISHNA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/2_PREFACE_SIVARAMAKRISHNA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/2_PREFACE_SIVARAMAKRISHNA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This edition of the Svarasiddhantacandrika is the result of my collated study of eight Manuscripts, the chief of which is Ms. obtained by me long ago from Maduras though a good number of readings have been taken from other manuscripts. Ms. belongs to M. R. Ry. K.. S. Narasimha Sastri Avl., Chidambaram, which was originally in the possession of the late MM. Harihara Sastrigal Avl., Chidambaram. is an incomplete palm leaf Ms. owned by M. R. Ry. S. Ramasubba Sastri Avl., Senior Pandit in Sanskrit, Annamalai University. Ms. is that of M.R.Ry. N. Vaidyanatha Sastri Avl., Raja&amp;rsquo;s College, Tiruvadi. , a palm-leaf Ms., has been obtained from the Government Oriental Ms. Library, Madras, and (incomplete) and , also on cadjan leaves, from the Adyar Library. These documents supply us with a satisfactory and harmonious text, though corruptions of Vedic passages are patent in most of them. These Vedic passages as found in the Mss. are preserved in the text, but their correct forms and accents are given in the Index. Hence they are not included in the errata. The Svaramañjarīkāra (p. 26, 1. 22) mentioned in all the Mss. seems to be a mistake for the Vṛttikara. It is noteworthy that the Värttika-tricakrādīnām chandasyupasankhyanam-is found in none of the Mss. It is highly gratifying that sufficient material is available for this edition of a most valuable commentary on the much neglected Svarasutras of Panin&amp;rsquo;. In spite of careful proof-reading errors have crept in for which, I regret, I myself am mostly responsible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३ FOREWORD KUPPUSWAMI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/3_FOREWORD_KUPPUSWAMI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/3_FOREWORD_KUPPUSWAMI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BY&#xA;MAHAMAHOPADHYAYA S. KUPPUSWAMI SASTRIGAL,&#xA;M.A., I.E.S. (Retired)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Honorary Professor of Sanskrit and Dean of the Faculty of Oriental Studies, Annamalai University.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Svarasiddhantacandrika by Srinivasa Dikṣita is a copious and complete commentary on the Svarasutras of Panini. The author was a disciple of Ramabhadra Dikṣita, a famous grammarian and poet, who flourished in the village called Tiruviśalur, on the bank of the Kaveri, in the Tanjore District, towards the close of the seventeenth century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४ विषयः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/4_viShayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/4_viShayaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;उपोद्घातः&#xA;English Introduction&#xA;आरम्भणप्रकरणम्&#xA;संज्ञाप्रकरणम्&#xA;परिभाषाप्रकरणम्&#xA;विषयसूचिका&#xA;पृष्ठाङ्काः&#xA;ixxxv&#xA;xxxvii—lvii&#xA;१&#xA;६&#xA;२०&#xA;संहितास्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;धातुखरप्रकरणम्&#xA;प्रत्ययस्वरप्रकरणम् ७१ - १५०&#xA;सुप्पित्स्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;तिङस्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;४७&#xA;६५&#xA;७७&#xA;त्रिनित्स्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;चित्स्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;कित्स्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;तिल्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;लित्स्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;रिस्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;चित्स्वराद्यपवादप्रकरणम्&#xA;समासखरप्रकरणम् १५१ -३५८.&#xA;बहुव्रीहिस्वरप्रकरणम् तत्पुरुषे पूर्वपदप्रकृतिस्वर प्रकरणम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;१०२&#xA;११३&#xA;१२८.&#xA;१३०&#xA;१३१&#xA;१३८&#xA;१४०&#xA;99&#xA;विषयः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तृतीया पूर्वपदप्रकृतिस्वरापवादः&#xA;सप्तमी पूर्वपदप्रकृतिस्वरापवादः&#xA;TET:&#xA;ناری ؟&#xA;१७६&#xA;अव्ययपूर्वपदप्रकृतिस्वगपवादः&#xA;त्रिविध कृत्स्त्ररापवादः&#xA;&amp;lsquo;थाथादिस्वरापवादः&#xA;دو&#xA;१९४&#xA;१९५&#xA;कृत्स्वरस्यैवापवादः&#xA;२०१&#xA;औणादिककृत्स्वरापवादः&#xA;२०६&#xA;अव्ययपूर्वपदप्रकृतिस्वर-&#xA;कृत्स्वरयोरपवादः&#xA;२०८&#xA;समासस्वरापवादः (तत्पुरुषस्वरः )&#xA;२१०&#xA;अव्ययीभावस्वरः&#xA;२४६&#xA;द्वन्द्वस्वरः&#xA;२४८&#xA;बहुव्रीह्यादिस्वरापवादः&#xA;२५३&#xA;फिट्सूत्राणि&#xA;२५९&#xA;सुबन्तसर्वानुदात्तप्रकरणम्&#xA;२८९&#xA;तिङन्तसर्वानुदात्तप्रकरणम्&#xA;३१८&#xA;प्लुत स्वरप्रकरणम्&#xA;३४९&#xA;एकश्रुतिप्रकरणम्&#xA;३७१&#xA;अष्टाध्यायीसूत्रसूची&#xA;३८९&#xA;फिटसूत्रसूची&#xA;३९६&#xA;वार्त्तिकसूची&#xA;३९९&#xA;परिभाषासूची&#xA;४००&#xA;वैदिकवाक्यसूची&#xA;४०१&#xA;निर्दिष्टप्रन्थग्रन्थकर्तृनामानि&#xA;४६५&#xA;शुद्धिपत्रिका&#xA;४६९&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५ उपोद्घातः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/5_upodghAtaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/5_upodghAtaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;शब्दः प्रकृतिः सर्ववर्णानाम्&amp;rsquo; ( तै. प्रा. xxii. 1.) &amp;lsquo;सर्ववर्णानां शब्दः – ध्वनिः - मूलकारणं भवति&amp;rsquo; (त्रिभाष्यरत्नम् )&#xA;द्वयी शक्तिर्मनुष्यस्य वर्णोत्पादने ध्वन्युत्पादने च ।&#xA;ध्वनिः प्रथमं व्यवहारसाधनम्&#xA;तमनुकर्तुं प्रयतते ।&#xA;प्रभवति&#xA;तत्र&#xA;जननसमकालमेत्र स वर्णोत्पादनसमर्थो न जायते तदनन्तरमेव तु पूर्वजातानां व्यवहारेषु क्रमेण व्युत्पद्यमानः&#xA;स्वयमपि&#xA;तथा यतमानोऽपि न झटित्येव तस्मै तत्सामर्थ्यमात्मनि पुनःपुनरभ्यस्यंस्तु कालेन विन्दति । नैवं ध्वनौ, जात एव हि शिशुः क्षुधाद्युपद्रुतो रौति । उपद्रवे उत्कटे अल्पे वा तदनुगुणं ध्वनिमपि उच्च नीचं वा जनयति । अतोऽस्य तदुत्पादनशक्तिः सहजा निरपेक्षा च । वर्णोत्पादनसामर्थ्यं पुनरभ्यासाधेयम् । सहजशक्तिश्च आधेयशक्तेः पूर्वमेव कार्यकरणाय अलमिति वर्णोत्पत्तेः पूर्वभावी ध्वनिः&amp;rsquo; ।।&#xA;अत एव वर्णोच्चारणशक्तिहीना अपि तिर्यञ्चः बालमूकादयश्च । दृश्यन्ते शब्दैकसाध्यान् व्यवहारान् ध्वनिभिरेव&#xA;व्यवहारान् ध्वनिभिरेव निर्वर्तयन्ति हि पशुपक्ष्यादयः सजातीयानाह्वातुम्, शज्यागमनमन्यानवगमयितुम्, अन्यैः पराभवे स्वेषाम् उपद्रवं बोधयितुं च नियतान् ध्वनीनाश्रयन्तः, तत इतरेषां प्रवृत्तिनिवृत्त्यादयश्च जायमानाः । तथा बालमूकादयोऽपि परस्परसमागमे जाते न शिलापुत्रका इव आसते, किन्तु कथञ्चित् ध्वनिभिर्बोधयन्तो बुध्यन्तश्च ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६ INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/6_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/svaraH/shrInivAsa-svara-siddhAnta-chandrikA/00/6_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabda (tone) is the origin of all sounds&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;Of all Varnas (sounds) dhvani (tone) is the root-cause&amp;rdquo;.2&#xA;Dhvani the original means of communication of ideas.&#xA;Man is endowed with the two powers of producing (1) the articulate sound and (2) the tone. By mere birth he is not able to produce the articulate sound; only after closely observing the conversations of his elders does he try to imitate them. Even in this attempt he does not all on a sudden become an adept but only after exerting himself for long in that direction. The case of tone, however, is different. A new-born child afflicted by hunger cries out; as its suffering is much or slight, it cries aloud or in a low tone. This capacity of the child to produce different tones is, therefore, innate; while the capacity to produce articulate sound is acquired by constant practice. The former power being independent manifests itself before the acquired power begins to operate. Hence man&amp;rsquo;s tone is anterior to articulate sound.3&#xA;Tone is the means of communication for those who have no power of speech. We observe that animals and birds convey their thoughts by gestures and tones. In some cases tone alone is employed, since gestures serve no purpose in the absence of company. Men also make use of tones in their dealings with animals and birds; so do children and dumb people. Hence tones are the means of communication when language and gestures fail. To this effect Hari says-&amp;quot; Tones, it is observed, influence the actions of animals, etc.&amp;quot; Hence modern Philologists accept the view that language has developed from tones, as may be inferred from the attempts of animals and children to convey their ideas, s&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
