<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A fine point in kR^iShNa yajur vedic recitation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2009-07-08_a-fine-point-in-krishna-yajur-vedic-recitation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2009-07-08_a-fine-point-in-krishna-yajur-vedic-recitation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2009/07/08/a-fine-point-in-krishna-yajur-vedic-recitation/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For a general account of vedic accents and their oral rendering one might refer to the following: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2008/09/01/a-practical-guide-to-vvedic-svara-s-in-recitation/&#34;&gt;vaidika svara-s.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The recitation of the R^igveda, the vulgate atharvaveda and kANva shAkha of the shukla yajur veda follow a generally similar pattern over much of bhArata-varSha. The nambuthiri-s of the chera country, especially while reciting the RV follow a highly derived set of rules that are encountered nowhere else. The widespread mAdhyaMdina-s and the Orissan paippalAda-s have largely lost the original svara-s and have only a pseudo-intoned recitation. The common pattern of the RV, the AV-vulgate and kANVa-SYV (not their shatapatha brAhmaNa) is the elongation of all long vowels and anunAsika consonants with associated svarita-s. Further, all these traditions render short vowel svarita by raising the pitch and exaggeratedly stressing the vowel. A deviation from this latter trend in short vowel svarita-s is only encountered in the R^ivedin-s from the mahArATTa country. In evolutionary terms the general pattern shared by these recitations appears to be the ancestral state of the rendering of the vedic text (contra what some white indologists and their fellow travelers had mistakenly thought it was).+++(V: Disagree)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical-guide-vedic-recitation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/practical-guide-vedic-recitation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/practical-guide-vedic-recitation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.files.wordpress.com/2008/09/svaras_new.pdf&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A practical guide to Svaras in Vedic recitation&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vedic-accents-and-their-vocal-rendering&#34;&gt;Vedic accents and their vocal rendering&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Udātta-s(U) are marked in red in this article. This is the natural or inherent accent in a word. Traditionally it is rendered as middle pitch. Udātta may be signaled especially in ṚV and AV traditions by raising the hand. Hence, Pāṇini’s sūtra on Udātta (उच्चैरुदात्तः - 1.2.29) originally meant that the arm was raised rather than the pitch being raised (as commonly understood by many). +++(V: Disagree)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Staal nambUtiri claim</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/staal_nambUtiri-claim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/shixA/svaraH/articles/MT_lekhAH/staal_nambUtiri-claim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frits Staal made a claim that certain nambUtiri-s recite udAtta in high-pitch pada &amp;amp; &amp;ldquo;ratha-pATha&amp;rdquo;. He claimed this was retention of ancestral style of veda recitation or even accented Skt speech as recorded by pANini’s statement of &amp;ldquo;ucchair udAttaH | All other veda recitation, including nambUtiri&amp;rsquo;s reciting taittirIya only raise svarita nor udAtta.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Staal claims that this is a post pANini development that spread throughout India. We hold that this hypothesis is not parsimonious &amp;amp; hence, flawed especially given that svarita is most conserved feature of veda recitation. Hence, uchchair udAttaH remains an unsolved problem with likely meaning being simply hand gesture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
