<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Goldman on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Goldman on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/00/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/00/</guid>
      <description>देववाणीप्रवेशिका Devavāṇīpraveśikā
AN INTRODUCTION TO THE SANSKRIT LANGUAGE
Third Edition
Robert P. Goldman and Sally J. Sutherland Goldman
To our students and our teachers
नहि सुशिक्षितो ऽपि नटबटुः स्वस्कन्धमारोढुं पटुः
&amp;ldquo;No matter how well-trained the tumbler&amp;rsquo;s boy, he will never be able to stand on his own shoulders.&amp;rdquo;
About the Authors Robert P. Goldman received his Ph.D. from the University of Penn sylvania in 1971. He is Professor of Sanskrit and Chair of the Center for South Asian Studies at the University of California at Berkeley, where he has taught Sanskrit for many years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 Phonology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/01_Phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/01_Phonology/</guid>
      <description>01 Phonology
1.0
The Sanskrit language, like any other natural language, has for its irreducible units a series of articulable sounds. These can be represented by a series of abstract graphic symbols. There are various systems of such symbols (scripts), but the one with which we will be chiefly concerned is known as the devanāgari (or nāgari) lipi (script), the vehicle of the overwhelming ma jority of printed Sanskrit texts. There are two interesting features of this script and the phonetic system of Sanskrit that make them in some ways easier to learn and memorize than English and its use of the roman script.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 The देवनागरी Script</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/02_The_devanAgarI_Script/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/02_The_devanAgarI_Script/</guid>
      <description>02 The देवनागरी Script
2.0
2.1
Learning the nāgari script is made somewhat simpler by the fact noted above (1.1) of each letter&amp;rsquo;s representing one, and only one, phonetic entity.
The script with its correct transliteration is as follows: FC (svara):
अ = a …
औ = au *This sound, vocalic !, is articulated as an 1 preceding the vowel s. It is almost non-existent in Sanskrit and you need not be too concerned with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 सन्धि</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/03_sandhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/03_sandhi/</guid>
      <description>03 सन्धि
3.0
3.1
Perhaps the most peculiar, and initially dismaying, feature of Sanskrit is its complex system of conditional phonological change known as U (sandhi), or combination. Various kinds of environmentally conditioned change occur in all languages, but no other has so formalized and systematized them as has
Sanskrit. There are two basic applications of the afu (sandhi) rules, depending on the circumstances under which the sound changes occur. Many of the same rules hold for both applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Parts of Speech and the Sanskrit Sentence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/04_Parts_of_Speech_and_the_Sanskrit_Sentence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/04_Parts_of_Speech_and_the_Sanskrit_Sentence/</guid>
      <description>04 Parts of Speech and the Sanskrit Sentence
4.0
4.1
4.2
Conjugation of Verbs; Declension of Nouns and Pronouns Despite the fact that Sanskrit preserves many formal distinc tions no longer maintained in English, it expresses ideas in sentences that are in many ways quite close to English sen tences. A grammatical sentence in either language normally requires that certain categories be filled, either explicitly or implicitly. All the words of the Sanskrit language may be divided roughly into three basic types.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 स्त्रीलिङ्ग Feminine Nouns in आ ; चतुर्थी, पञ्चमी and सप्तमी विभक्ति-s; Demonstrative Pronouns</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/05_strIlinga_Feminine_Nouns_in_A_chaturthI_panchamI_and_saptamI_vibhakti-s_Demonstrative_Pronouns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/05_strIlinga_Feminine_Nouns_in_A_chaturthI_panchamI_and_saptamI_vibhakti-s_Demonstrative_Pronouns/</guid>
      <description>05 स्त्रीलिङ्ग Feminine Nouns in आ ; चतुर्थी, पञ्चमी and सप्तमी विभक्ति-s; Demonstrative Pronouns
5.0
5.1
एक°
द्वि dvi°
bahu
In addition to the पुंलिङ्ग (purnlinga-masculine) and नपुंसकलिङ्ग (napunsakalinga-neuter) nouns in -अ (-a), there is an impor tant class of स्त्रीलिङ्ग (strilinga-feminine) nouns in -आ (-a). Some of these nouns are related in meaning to some of the पुलिङ्ग (pumlinga-masculine) nouns in -अ (-a). Examples: ales: (bālah) boy 10 (bālā) girl सुतः (sutah) son सुता (sutā) daughter The paradigm is as follows: dell (kanyā) girl, daughter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Nominal Stems in -इ and -उ; Interrogative, Relative, and Correlative Clauses: The क्-य-त् Series of Indeclinables and Pronouns</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/06_Nominal_Stems_in_-i_and_-u_Interrogative_Relative_and_Correlative_Clauses_The_k-ya-t_Series_of_Indeclinables_and_Pronouns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/06_Nominal_Stems_in_-i_and_-u_Interrogative_Relative_and_Correlative_Clauses_The_k-ya-t_Series_of_Indeclinables_and_Pronouns/</guid>
      <description>06 Nominal Stems in -इ and -उ; Interrogative, Relative, and Correlative Clauses: The क्-य-त् Series of Indeclinables and Pronouns
6.0
6.1
एक
बहु
dvio
मुनयः
Sanskrit has a large number of nominal stems in short - (-i) and short -3 (-u) whose declensions are closely analogous. The nouns are of all genders, although gros (pumlinga) and स्त्रीलिङ्ग (strilinga) nouns in -इ (-i) arethe most important class. नपुंसकलिङ्ग (napunsakalinga)-इ (-i) stems and स्त्रीलिङ्ग (strilinga) -3 (-u) stems are relatively rare and, therefore, their paradigms are omitted here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 स्त्रीलिङ्ग (Feminine) Stems in ई; The गण-s of the Present System</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/07_strIlinga_Feminine_Stems_in_I_The_gaNa-s_of_the_Present_System/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/07_strIlinga_Feminine_Stems_in_I_The_gaNa-s_of_the_Present_System/</guid>
      <description>07 स्त्रीलिङ्ग (Feminine) Stems in ई; The गण-s of the Present System
7.0
7.1
बह
Aside from स्त्रीलिङ्ग (strilinga-feminine) stems in -आ (-३), ___ the most common स्त्रीलिङ्ग (strilinga-feminine) stem end
ing is -$ (-1). The paradigm is as follows: स्त्रीलिङ्ग (strilinga) -ई (-i) देवी (devi) lady, goddess वचन
एक
द्वि vacana → ekai ___dvi°
bahu°
विभक्ति vibhakti
देवी
देव्यौ
देव्यः devi
devyau devyaḥ देवीम् देव्यौ
देवीः devīm
devyau devīḥ देव्या</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Noun Stem Strength; Noun Stems in-अन्; अनद्यतनभूते लङ्, The Imperfect; उपसर्ग-s (Upasarga-s)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/08_Noun_Stem_Strength_Noun_Stems_in-an_anadyatanabhUte_la~N_The_Imperfect_upasarga-s_Upasarga-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/08_Noun_Stem_Strength_Noun_Stems_in-an_anadyatanabhUte_la~N_The_Imperfect_upasarga-s_Upasarga-s/</guid>
      <description>08 Noun Stem Strength; Noun Stems in-अन्; अनद्यतनभूते लङ्, The Imperfect; उपसर्ग-s (Upasarga-s)
8.0
8.1
All the noun stems introduced thus far have ended in vowels. This is not the case, however, with all nouns. Several classes of nouns have stems with consonant finals. These stems (and some vowel stems—see below, 10.0), unlike the nouns so far learned, have a distinction of stem strength.
Noun Stem Strength a. Of पुंलिङ्ग and स्त्रीलिङ्ग stems, the only strong forms are प्रथमा विभक्ति, एकवचन, द्विवचन, and बहुवचन.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Noun Stems in अः; The कर्मणि प्रयोग</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/09_Noun_Stems_in_aH_The_karmaNi_prayoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/09_Noun_Stems_in_aH_The_karmaNi_prayoga/</guid>
      <description>09 Noun Stems in अः; The कर्मणि प्रयोग
ar
9.0
Noun Stems in अः (ah) There is another important class of nouns whose stems end in अः (an). They are mostly नपुंसकलिङ्ग nouns, and their declen sion is a good example of a regular consonantal paradigm.
9.1
a. नपुंसकलिङ्ग; तपः (tapah-act of austerity)
एक
तपः
tapah
तपः tapah
तपसा tapasā
बहु तपांसि tapāmsi तपांसि tapāmsi तपोभिः tapobhiḥ तपोभ्यः tapobhyah तपोभ्यः tapobhyaḥ</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Nominal Stems in - ऋ; Verbal Adjectives; भूते कृदन्तः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/10_Nominal_Stems_in_-_R_Verbal_Adjectives_bhUte_kRdantaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/10_Nominal_Stems_in_-_R_Verbal_Adjectives_bhUte_kRdantaH/</guid>
      <description>10 Nominal Stems in - ऋ; Verbal Adjectives; भूते कृदन्तः
10.0
There is relatively small but important group of nouns whose stems end in the vowel &amp;ndash; (). This group is divisible into two closely similar subgroups with slightly different declensions. Nouns of these declensions are unlike other nouns in final vow els in that they show the system of stem strength typical of consonant final stems. i. The first, and much more restricted, of these subgroups con</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Stems in -अन्त; Adjectival Suffixes in-मन्त् and -वन्तः The क्तवतु (Past Active Participle); The त्वान्त, ल्यबन्त (Gerund); The लोट् (Imperative)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/11_Stems_in_-anta_Adjectival_Suffixes_in-mant_and_-vantaH_The_ktavatu_Past_Active_Participle_The_tvAnta_lyabanta_Gerund_The_loT_Imperative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/11_Stems_in_-anta_Adjectival_Suffixes_in-mant_and_-vantaH_The_ktavatu_Past_Active_Participle_The_tvAnta_lyabanta_Gerund_The_loT_Imperative/</guid>
      <description>11 Stems in -अन्त; Adjectival Suffixes in-मन्त् and -वन्तः The क्तवतु (Past Active Participle); The त्वान्त, ल्यबन्त (Gerund); The लोट् (Imperative)
11.0
11.1
Stems in -376 There are a number of nominal and adjectival stems in Sanskrit that end in the vowel 37 followed by the conjunct - These words fall into a very few fairly significant categories.
 Adjectives formed with the possessive suffixes -Hal and  -वन्त् (traditionally called मतुप् and वतुप respectively by the</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Nominal Stems in इन्; समास (Nominal Composition)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/12_Nominal_Stems_in_in_samAsa_Nominal_Composition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/12_Nominal_Stems_in_in_samAsa_Nominal_Composition/</guid>
      <description>12 Nominal Stems in इन्; समास (Nominal Composition)
12.0
The suffix -5 is used freely in Sanskrit to form adjectives or nouns that indicate that the thing denoted by the word to which the suffix is added is possessed by, or in some way an attribute of, the word that the newly formed adjective modifies. a. The suffix is normally used with noun stems in -31 or -371
and replaces the final vowel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 तुमनन्त (The Infinitive); समास Continued; बहुव्रीहि Application of कर्मधारय and तत्पुरुष समास-s, The द्विगु समास</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/13_tumananta_The_Infinitive_samAsa_Continued_bahuvrIhi_Application_of_karmadhAraya_and_tatpuruSha_samAsa-s_The_dvigu_samAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/13_tumananta_The_Infinitive_samAsa_Continued_bahuvrIhi_Application_of_karmadhAraya_and_tatpuruSha_samAsa-s_The_dvigu_samAsa/</guid>
      <description>13 तुमनन्त (The Infinitive); समास Continued; बहुव्रीहि Application of कर्मधारय and तत्पुरुष समास-s, The द्विगु समास
13.0
13.1
क
गन्तुम्
से
An extremely useful and simple indeclinable of an &amp;ldquo;infinitive&amp;rdquo; or dative &amp;ldquo;infinitive&amp;rdquo; value may be formed freely from virtu ally all roots in the language. a. Formation of the Infinitive
The characteristic and invariable marker of this formation is the suffix -94. Before this suffix, the root vowel is sub ject to JM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 समास Concluded; The द्वन्द्व and अव्ययीभाव समास-s; The विधि लिङ् (Optative)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/14_samAsa_Concluded_The_dvandva_and_avyayIbhAva_samAsa-s_The_vidhi_li~N_Optative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/14_samAsa_Concluded_The_dvandva_and_avyayIbhAva_samAsa-s_The_vidhi_li~N_Optative/</guid>
      <description>14 समास Concluded; The द्वन्द्व and अव्ययीभाव समास-s; The विधि लिङ् (Optative)
14.0
14.1
There remain two basic types of compounds to be examined. These are rather different from the preceding two types and their all applications, but they are extremely simple and require only the briefest treatment. The 6-6 H4 The first of these is the &amp;amp;&amp;amp; HATH, sometimes given the racy title of “copulative compound.&amp;quot; This compound differs from the basic कर्मधारय and तत्पुरुष types in that it does not consist of sets of pairs but is simply a stringing together of any number of nouns, which in ordinary syntax would be connected by the conjunctive particle 7 or, in rare cases, the disjunctive particle al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 वर्तमाने कृदन्तः (The Present Participle)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/15_vartamAne_kRdantaH_The_Present_Participle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/15_vartamAne_kRdantaH_The_Present_Participle/</guid>
      <description>15 वर्तमाने कृदन्तः (The Present Participle)
15.0
With the fara fess (optative) we learned the last verbal conju gation of the present system. However, there is still one participial (i.e., nominal) form based on the present stem. This form, the present participle, is of very common occurrence and great usefulness. It is, like the art and other non-conju gational verbal forms, an excellent example of classical Sanskrit&amp;rsquo;s tendency to depart from the false forms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Non-गण Conjugations; The लट्, लङ्, and लुट् (Future System and the Conditional); कृत्य (Gerundive)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/16_Non-gaNa_Conjugations_The_laT_la~N_and_luT_Future_System_and_the_Conditional_kRtya_Gerundive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/16_Non-gaNa_Conjugations_The_laT_la~N_and_luT_Future_System_and_the_Conditional_kRtya_Gerundive/</guid>
      <description>16 Non-गण Conjugations; The लट्, लङ्, and लुट् (Future System and the Conditional); कृत्य (Gerundive)
16.0
16.1
Thus far, all the finite verbal forms you have learned, with the exception of the artifot yet, have involved knowledge of the
10, or conjugation class, to which each US, or verbal root, belongs. These forms, the C, MS, and fuss are, more over, the only finite forms generated according to these M-s. The remaining verbal conjugations, then, whatever their own peculiarities, do not require that you know the m of a root in order to generate their forms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 परोक्षभूते लिट् (The Perfect); The Perfect Participle</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/17_paroxabhUte_liT_The_Perfect_The_Perfect_Participle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/17_paroxabhUte_liT_The_Perfect_The_Perfect_Participle/</guid>
      <description>17 परोक्षभूते लिट् (The Perfect); The Perfect Participle
17.0
17.1
17.2
The foc, or “perfect,&amp;quot; is the last of the finite verbal conjuga tions in very frequent use. Like the 5, it functions as a simple narrative past. The term “perfect,” like the term &amp;ldquo;imperfect,&amp;rdquo; was given to the form by Western philologists and has no sig nificance with regard to &amp;ldquo;aspect&amp;rdquo; or duration of action or states expressed The traditional Indian grammatical texts do attempt to distin guish the functions of the two forms (5 and foc).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 णिजन्त, सवन्त, and यङन्त Secondary Conjugations; नामधातु (The Denominative)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/18_Nijanta_savanta_and_ya~Nanta_Secondary_Conjugations_nAmadhAtu_The_Denominative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/18_Nijanta_savanta_and_ya~Nanta_Secondary_Conjugations_nAmadhAtu_The_Denominative/</guid>
      <description>18 णिजन्त, सवन्त, and यङन्त Secondary Conjugations; नामधातु (The Denominative)
18.0
18.1
18.2
With one exception, the characteristic signs of the various con jugated systems introduced thus far are alike in that they are markers only of tense or mode. In other words, the ten signs of the 10-s (7.4ff.), the -R4 of the future (16.2ff.), and the 328 (reduplication) of the perfect (17.Off.) suffice only to mark the general conjugation to which a verbal form belongs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 सर्वनामन् (Additional Pronouns); संख्या -s (Numerals); अद्यतनभूते लङ् (The Aorist Systems)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/19_sarvanAman_Additional_Pronouns_saMkhyA_-s_Numerals_adyatanabhUte_la~N_The_Aorist_Systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/19_sarvanAman_Additional_Pronouns_saMkhyA_-s_Numerals_adyatanabhUte_la~N_The_Aorist_Systems/</guid>
      <description>19 सर्वनामन् (Additional Pronouns); संख्या -s (Numerals); अद्यतनभूते लङ् (The Aorist Systems)
19.0
19.1
Additional Pronouns In addition to the pronominal stem तत् (सः, तत् , सा) (5.5ff.), Sanskrit has two important pronominal paradigms which you
must leam. Both are like तत् etc., in that they are demonstra tive, construe with verbs in the प्रथमपुरुष, and may serve in the senses of &amp;ldquo;the,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;this,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;that.&amp;rdquo; The stems are: 1) अयम् (m), इदम् (n), इयम् (f), and 2) असौ (m), अदः (n), असौ (f).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 कृत् and तद्धित-प्रत्ययाः, च्वि, Nominal Derivation and Sanskrit Vocabulary</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/20_kRt_and_taddhita-pratyayAH_chvi_Nominal_Derivation_and_Sanskrit_Vocabulary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/20_kRt_and_taddhita-pratyayAH_chvi_Nominal_Derivation_and_Sanskrit_Vocabulary/</guid>
      <description>20 कृत् and तद्धित-प्रत्ययाः, च्वि, Nominal Derivation and Sanskrit Vocabulary
20.0
20.1
The grammatical complexity of Sanskrit is such that, in the first year, it tends to overshadow other areas of language learning, especially the acquisition of a working vocabulary. Nonetheless, the major features of the grammar will soon, through constant repetition, become quite familiar. Vocabulary, on the other hand, tends to loom as a greater issue when one begins reading Sanskrit texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Additional Consonantal Stem Formations; Stems with Final संयुक्त Vowels; Some Irregular Nominal Declensions; Declension of the Comparative Suffix यांस्, यः; Some Remarks on Adverbial Formation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/21_Additional_Consonantal_Stem_Formations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/21_Additional_Consonantal_Stem_Formations/</guid>
      <description>21 Additional Consonantal Stem Formations; Stems with Final संयुक्त Vowels; Some Irregular Nominal Declensions; Declension of the Comparative Suffix यांस्, यः; Some Remarks on Adverbial Formation
21.0
21.1
Aside from the nominal stems with final consonants already introduced, there is a class of nouns ending in one or another of the simple consonants. These nouns are most often mono syllabic and derive either from a root with only the 1994, or zero, suffix (20.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 Readings from the वाल्मीकि-रामायणम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/22_Readings_from_the_vAlmIki-rAmAyaNam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/22_Readings_from_the_vAlmIki-rAmAyaNam/</guid>
      <description>22 Readings from the वाल्मीकि-रामायणम्
22.0
The following verses are excerpted from the first of the वाल्मीकि रामायण. In the passage the divine sage नारद, in re sponse to desilta&amp;rsquo;s questions, relates, very concisely, the tale of &amp;lt;TH. It is on the basis of this narration that is hift, inspired, discovers poetry and composes the रामायण.
The verses selected complete the story in outline, from the abduction of Hial to the end.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GLOSSARY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/GLOSSARY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/goldman/GLOSSARY/</guid>
      <description>GLOSSARY
-अ
-a
(Arabic Numerals following definitions refer to Lessons.)
अ- अन्
अङ्गीकृ a-, an&amp;ndash;negative prefix for nomi- angikr (8P) accept, agree to (20)
nal or indeclinable forms: un-, | अचिरान non-, without-, -less (14)
acirāt (ind)—shortly, soon (12) अकम्पनः
अजित akampanah (m prop)-name of a
ajita (adj)—unconquered (14) raksasa (20)
अञ्जलिः अकृत
anjalih (m)–gesture of reverence akrta (adj)—undone
or supplication made by plac अक्षरम्
ing the palms together (16) aksaram (n)-syllable, sound, अन.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
