<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>21st century learning - shashi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/shashikiraNa_21stce-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/shashikiraNa_21stce-approach/</guid>
      <description>This paper by Shashi Kiran B N and Hari Ravikumar was presented at the international conference New Frontiers in Sanskrit and Indic Knowledge in June 2017 organized by the Chinmaya International Foundation.
Abstract Sanskrit, one of the greatest gifts of India to the world, is unique in many ways. The Pāṇinian system of grammar, logical in its structure and exhaustive in its delineation, gave the language great strength in terms of word-generation ability, brevity, and freedom from ambiguity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Munshi 1951 speech</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/munshi_1951_speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/munshi_1951_speech/</guid>
      <description>Intro  I -  Of all the forces which bind the man and make him a social and cultural being, the most powerful is the ‘Word,’ In that sense, the worship of the Word, Sabda-Brahma, is one of the most all-pervading forces of life. For instance, geographically India owes everything to the Himalayas; in the sphere of social relationships, the mind and the spirit, India owes everything to Sanskrit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RS - Lanka sanskrit</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/seneviratne_lanka-sanskrit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/seneviratne_lanka-sanskrit/</guid>
      <description>Source - Colombo Telegraph .
What makes one a Sanskrit scholar today?
What areas of the Sanskrit language does one need to be good with to declare “I know Sanskrit”?
Can one become knowledgeable about Sanskrit scholarship without mastering the language?
What could Sanskrit tell us and could not?
Do we really need Sanskrit?
The questions of this sort demand clarification of a few points before being answered. First, Sanskrit scholarship has been a misnomer mainly because one cannot, justifiably, know a certain language without knowing the wealth of knowledge in it, simply because knowledge comes to us getting on a certain language, either oral, written or both, as the vehicle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spoken-sanskrit-western-perspective</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/spoken-sanskrit-western-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/spoken-sanskrit-western-perspective/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Spoken Sanskrit
January 9, 2016 @ 8:54 pm · Filed by Victor Mair under Language and culture, Language and education, Language and literature, Vernacular
From December 13-17, 2015, I participated in an international workshop at the Israel Institute for Advanced Studies (IIAS) on the Edmond J. Safra campus of Hebrew University in Jerusalem. The title of the workshop was &amp;ldquo;A Lasting Vision: Dandin’s Mirror in the World of Asian Letters&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>who-killed-sanskrit</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/who-killed-sanskrit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/who-killed-sanskrit/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
विश्वास-टिप्पनी Some of the points are addressed in misconceptions page ; will expand to encompass accusation of brAhmaNa hypocracy/ incompetence.
 Doniger, Truschke, Pollock didn’t ‘kill’ Sanskrit. Brahmins did
Indian Americans who have written &amp;lsquo;Ten Heads of Ravana&amp;rsquo; aim to decolonise the Indian mindset. Why do they not send their children to Sanskrit schools in India but to prestigious universities in US?
10 June, 2023
A group of mostly Indian Americans led by Rajiv Malhotra recently published a book called Ten Heads of Ravana: A Critique of Hinduphobic Scholars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>रङ्गनाथलेखमञ्जूषा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/ranganAtha-lekhA-manjUShA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/ranganAtha-lekhA-manjUShA/</guid>
      <description>प्रस्तावः रङ्गनाथलेखमञ्जूषा
संस्कृतभारती, बेङ्गलूरु
रङ्गनाथलेखमञ्जूषा
(महामहोपाध्यायस्य विदुषः एन्. रङ्गनाथशर्मवर्यस्य गद्यलेखानां सङ्ग्रहः) संस्कृतभारती
बेङ्गलूरु
आशीर्वचनं श्ङ्गेरीयतेः ।। श्री शृङ्गेरी-श्रीजगद्गुरु-महासंस्थानम् ।।
श्रीमत्-परमहंस-परिव्राजकाचार्य-वर्य-पद-वाक्य-प्रमाण-पारावार-पारीण-
यम-नियमासन-प्राणायाम-प्रत्याहार-धारणा-ध्यान-समाध्य्-अष्टाङ्ग-योगानुष्ठान-निष्ठ-
तपश्-चक्रवर्त्य्-अनाद्य्-अविच्छिन्न-श्रीशङ्कराचार्य-गुरुपरम्परा-प्राप्त-षड्-दर्शन-स्थापनाचार्य-
व्याख्यान-सिंहासनाधीश्वर
सकल-निगमागम-सार-हृदय-सांख्य-त्रय-प्रतिपादक-
वैदिक-मार्ग-प्रवर्तक-
सर्व-तन्त्र-स्वतन्त्र-
आदि-राज-धानी-विद्या-नगर-महाराजधानी-कर्णाटक-सिंहासन-प्रतिष्ठापनाचार्य-
श्रीमद्-राजाधिराज-गुरु-
भूमण्डलाचार्य-
ऋष्य-शृङ्ग-पुर-वराधीश्वर-
तुङ्ग-भद्रा-तीर-वासि-
श्रीमद्-विद्या-शङ्कर-पाद-पद्माराधक-
श्री-जगद्-गुरु-श्रीमद्-अभिनव-विद्या-तीर्थ-स्वामि-गुरु-कर-कमल-सञ्जात-
श्री-जगद्गुरु-शृङ्गेरी-श्रीमद्-भारती-तीर्थ-महास्वामिभिः ।।
निखिलास्तिक-महाजनेषु नारायण-स्मरण-पुरस्सरं विरचिता आशिषस् समुल्लसन्तु ।।
यशःकायाः विद्वद्-धौरेयाः श्री-यन्-रङ्गनाथ-शर्माणः व्याकरणादि-दर्शनेषु अनितर-साधारण-पाण्डिती-मण्डिता आसन् । तत्रापि पाणिनीये तन्त्रे तेषाम् अस्खलिता गतिर् आसीत् । गैर्वाण्यां कार्णाटक्यां च नैकान् निबन्धान निबध्य जनतायै महतीम् उपकृतिम् अतानिषुः । अनवद्ये गद्ये हृद्ये पद्येऽपि ते सममेव लेखनीं व्यापारयामासुः । नैकासु पत्रिकासु प्रकटित-चराणि तदीयानि लेखनानि अन्तेवसतां व्युत्पत्तिम् इव विदुषां चेतसश् चमत्-कृतिम् अप्य् आदधति स्म ।+++(5)+++ सुरभारत्या महिमानुवर्णने तस्या आवश्यकता-प्रतिपादने तस्या अक्लिष्टता निरूपणे च ते नितराम् अभिनिविशन्ते स्म । तादृशान् लेखान् तत इतस् समुद्धत्य संस्कृतभारती ग्रन्थरूपेण प्रकाशयतीति विदित्वा अत्यर्थं मोदामहे । निबन्धोऽयं सुरभारती-प्रणयिनो नितराम् आप्याययिष्यतीति प्रतीमो वयम् । श्रीशारदा-शशि-शकल-शेखरयोर् असीमया कृपया ग्रन्थोऽयं विशिष्टं प्रचारम् एत्व् इत्य् आशास्महे ।</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>लङ्कायां संस्कृतम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/lanka_education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/lanka_education/</guid>
      <description>Below are excerpts from Rohana Seneviratne&amp;rsquo;s article.
 &amp;ldquo;Buddhist monks from their early Samanera age, are “required” to learn Sanskrit alongside Pali &amp;hellip; it is Pali – not Sanskrit – that is expected to sustain the local version of Theravada Buddhism on this land.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;The academic contexts where Sanskrit is taught in support of the study of disciplines such as the Sinhala and Tamil languages and literature, History, Religious Studies, Archaeology, and Philosophy often confine Sanskrit scholarship to the basics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
