<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>4 1 Aṅgādhikāra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_1_angAdhikAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_1_angAdhikAra/</guid>
      <description>Before I examine examples of rule interaction at the same step in tiṄ and kr̥t derivations, I will examine rules 6.4.1 aṅgasya and 1.4.13 yasmāt pratyayavidhis tadādi pratyaye’ṅgam which play a pivotal role in running Pāṇini’s grammatical machine.
6.4.1 aṅgasya is an adhikāra (heading) sūtra, the jurisdiction of which continues all the way up to the end of 7.4. Pāṇini defines the term aṅga in
 1.4.13 yasmāt pratyayavidhis tadādi pratyaye’ṅgam.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 2 Examples of Application of 1 4 13 and 6 4 1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_2_Examples_of_Application_of_1_4_13_and_6_4_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_2_Examples_of_Application_of_1_4_13_and_6_4_1/</guid>
      <description>Now I will discuss some examples through which I will show that my interpretation of 1.4.13 and 6.4.1 alone can help us derive the correct final form. But first, let me offer a clarification.
In many of the examples discussed in this chapter, the derivation should begin with: verbal base + lakāra. At this stage, there are two possibilities:
(i) only one rule, i.e., the rule which teaches the replacement of the lakāra is applicable, and this rule applies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 3 Examples of DOI Conflict</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_3_Examples_of_DOI_Conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_3_Examples_of_DOI_Conflict/</guid>
      <description>Now I will discuss examples of DOI conflict, which are of interest to the tradition, and show how my interpretation of 1.4.2 is able to solve these cases. I will also consistently apply my interpretations of 1.4.13 and 6.4.1 respectively in all these examples.
In each example, I will prove the existence of DOI conflict and apply my interpretation of 1.4.2 to solve it. As stated in chapter 2, generally speaking, to deal with examples of DOI conflict, the tradition uses nityatva (for cases of unidirectional blocking), niravakāśatva or its interpretation of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 4 Examples of SOI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_4_Examples_of_SOI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_4_Examples_of_SOI/</guid>
      <description>We have already looked at several examples of SOI while discussing examples of DOI conflict. Here I will present a few more examples. As I have done earlier, I will spell out and examine the conditions in which the rules apply and then determine which of the two rules is more specific.
(1) cal + tiP – ‘to walk’, simple future third-person singular
cal + tiP
3.1.33 3.1.68
3.1.33 syatāsī lr̥luṭoḥ: affixes sya and tāsI respectively occur after verbal roots when LR̥ and LUṬ follow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 5 Selection of Examples</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_5_Selection_of_Examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_5_Selection_of_Examples/</guid>
      <description>I have presented examples of both SOI conflict and DOI conflict in chapters 2, 3 and 4, of this thesis. Instead of focusing on only those steps that involve conflict, I have performed entire derivations, right from the first step to the last one – drawing diagrams for each step where two or more rules are simultaneously applicable. Before closing this chapter, I must discuss the process through which I conducted my searches for examples, the rationale behind the choice of these examples and also the distributional patterns I noticed in this process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 6 Distribution of Examples of Conflict</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_6_Distribution_of_Examples_of_Conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/04/4_6_Distribution_of_Examples_of_Conflict/</guid>
      <description>Now let us examine the distribution of examples of conflict across various kinds of derivations (e.g., subanta, kr̥danta etc.). Since Pāṇini uses the general-exception framework throughout the Aṣṭādhyāyī, we find cases of SOI conflict in all kinds of derivations. And while we might find more examples of SOI conflict in some kinds of derivations than others, we do not come across any unique or peculiar patterns that merit discussion here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
