<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>dravidian in sanskrit: kumArIla</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/dravidian_in_sanskrit_kumArIla/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/dravidian_in_sanskrit_kumArIla/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://unrollthread.com/t/1223672610950529025/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Can someone kindly tell more about &amp;ldquo;Dravidian&amp;rdquo; words or hymns in Vedas?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, while kumArila-bhaTTa speaks of drAviDa words in veda &amp;amp; gives examples of non-Arya (drAviDa &amp;amp; others) words, he doesn&amp;rsquo;t specify which word is from where.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here is an excerpt from his commentary; towards the end, you can read, &amp;ldquo;tatheha pikanematAmarasAdi coditam&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. The term &amp;lsquo;coditam&amp;rsquo; indicates that those words (pika, nema, tAmarasa, etc) are found in the veda.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dravidian loans</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/dravidian-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/dravidian-loans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;phalam, &amp;ldquo;fruit&amp;rdquo; &amp;lt; *paḷam, &amp;ldquo;ripe fruit&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mukham, &amp;ldquo;mouth, face, beginning&amp;rdquo; &amp;lt; *mukam, &amp;ldquo;mouth, face, beginning&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;khala-, &amp;ldquo;threshing floor&amp;rdquo; &amp;lt; *kaḷam, &amp;ldquo;threshing floor&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;lāngalam, &amp;ldquo;plow&amp;rdquo; &amp;lt; *ñāṅgal, &amp;ldquo;plow&amp;rdquo; (in my opinion, ñāṅgal is originally a compound of Proto-Dravidian *ñāḷ, &amp;ldquo;earth, ground&amp;rdquo; + *kaḷ, &amp;ldquo;to dig, excavate&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ukham, &amp;ldquo;hip&amp;rdquo; &amp;lt; *ukkam, &amp;ldquo;hip&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kāṇa-, &amp;ldquo;blind in one eye&amp;rdquo; &amp;lt; *kāṇ-, &amp;ldquo;to see&amp;rdquo; + negative marker *-aH-, &amp;ldquo;to see not&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kaṭuka-, &amp;ldquo;pungent, bitter&amp;rdquo; &amp;lt; *kaṭu &amp;ldquo;pungent, bitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LR Vaidya front</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/lr-vaidya-front/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/lr-vaidya-front/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;preface&#34;&gt;PREFACE.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When already there are some Sanskrit-English Dictionaries in the field, it becomes necessary to explain, at the outset, the necessity for the production of such a volume as the one now offered to the public. Of the Sanskrit-English Dictionaries, now in existence, none was written specially to meet the wants of Indian students and none is within the easy reach of the student of moderate means. Professor Goldstücker’s excellent but voluminous lexicon did not even reach the end of अ and is now out of print. Prof. M. Williams’ Sanskrit-English Dictionary is undoubtedly a highly useful and meritorious production in many respects. But it abounds in matter not needful to the ordinary student of classics; its plan and arrangement, though philosophical, are not practical; and it takes up much unnecessary space by the employment of Roman character in addition to the Devanāgarī, by giving insertion to unnecessary forms, and by repeating, in every instance, the leading word in the collocation of compounds. It is, besides, so highly priced as to be practically within the reach of very few indeed. Prof. Benfey’s Dictionary, not to speak of its very high price, contains much useless matter and is often singularly wanting in that which the student would naturally look for in a Dictionary. Prof. Wilson’s Dictionary gives mere synonyms, is defective in its treatment of verbs and generally fails to supply to the student the additional information he seeks. Moreover, being an old attempt, it is superseded by the performances of later writers. Of course, I do not mean to disparage these works; on the other hand, I value them highly and I have elsewhere acknowledged my obligations to them. I only wish to show that the Indian student of Sanskrit classics is thus left without any Sanskrit-English Dictionary, which, being within his easy reach, would satisfy his ordinary demands. While lecturing to Sanskrit classes at College, this want of a suitable Sanskrit-English Dictionary was often brought to my notice; and, last year, I was prevailed upon by my publisher to undertake to prepare the present work, chiefly to meet the ordinary demands of High School and College students. My chief objective, accordingly, in compiling the present Dictionary, has been to produce a volume of moderate size, as cheap and handy as possible without sacrifice of clearness and facility of reference, which the student can command at any time and place and in which he would find all that he ordinarily requires.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Onomatopoeia</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/headword-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/headword-choice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: सुहासः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My preference is to avoid modernisms and try to reuse existing words and word construction paradigms as much as possible. Especially if new coinages clash with established ones. For instance, हा हा has the established meaning of sorrow, so I would not use it in the book for laughter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most onomatopoeia in Sanskrit is outside of the main canon (Kalidasa, Bana etc.). The frequency is greater in Jaina literature and in authors like Rajashekhara who engaged with Prakrit. The frequency is greater in Prakrit, and even greater in Apabhramsha which really loves onomatopoeia. As translators into Sanskrit, we should be drawing upon the entire Sanskritic tradition to find the words that we need. &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.56612/page/n173/mode/1up&#34;&gt;This is a big list of onomatopoeias&lt;/a&gt; found in the Mahapurana of Pushpadanta. It should also not be difficult to grep through a text corpus to make a list of such usages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synonymity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/synonymity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/synonymity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;विस्तारः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्)&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DHH Ingalls observes one reason for this strength of Sanskrit&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit not only has an enormous vocabulary; it has also a larger choice of synonyms than any other language I know. In a natural language there are probably no synonyms.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of course, one can go to a thesaurus and find what are called synonyms. For the English word &amp;lsquo;house&amp;rsquo; one may find ‘dwelling,&amp;rsquo; ‘residence,&amp;rsquo; ‘tenement,&amp;rsquo; ‘abode,&amp;rsquo; and so on. But these are not true synonyms as one can see the moment one tries to interchange them. One cannot say of the Vanderbilts that they lived in a large tenement in Newport, Rhode Island. Each word in English has connotations that it cannot shed and that permit it to be used only in an appropriate social and emotional setting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>वृष्टि-वचनम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/vRShTi-vachanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/vRShTi-vachanam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;स्रोतः - सुहासः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Expressions for Rainfall in Sanskrit  -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Standard Expression -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;देवो वर्षति -  The Deva [of rain] makes it rain.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Variations of Rainfall Descriptions -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;गात्रस्नायं (or पुरुषस्नायं) वर्षति देवः -  It rains enough to bathe one&amp;rsquo;s body.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;चेलक्नोपं वर्षति देवः (or वस्त्रक्नोपं वर्षति देवः or वसनक्नोपं वर्षति देवः) -  It rains enough to wet a cloth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;क्नोपम् -  From the rare verb क्नूय् meaning &amp;ldquo;to be wet&amp;rdquo; (See, ashtadhyayi.com/sutraani/3/4/33 )&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;गोष्पदपूरं वृष्टो देवः -  It rained enough to fill the impression of a cow&amp;rsquo;s hoof.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>शब्दानुकृतिः Onomatopoeia</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/onomatopoeia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/koshaH/articles/onomatopoeia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: सुहासः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My preference is to avoid modernisms and try to reuse existing words and word construction paradigms as much as possible. Especially if new coinages clash with established ones. For instance, हा हा has the established meaning of sorrow, so I would not use it in the book for laughter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most onomatopoeia in Sanskrit outside of the main canon (Kalidasa, Bana etc.). The frequency is greater in Jaina literature and in authors like Rajashekhara who engaged with Prakrit. The frequency is greater in Prakrit, and even greater in Apabhramsha which really loves onomatopoeia. As translators into Sanskrit, we should be drawing upon the entire Sanskritic tradition to find the words that we need. &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.56612/page/n173/mode/1up&#34;&gt;This is a big list of onomatopoeias&lt;/a&gt; found in the Mahapurana of Pushpadanta. It should also not be difficult to grep through a text corpus to make a list of such usages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
