<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अक्लूज्कराशोकः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/aklUjkaraH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अक्लूज्कराशोकः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/aklUjkaraH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Different sociolinguistics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/aklUjkaraH/Different_sociolinguistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/aklUjkaraH/Different_sociolinguistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Different Sociolinguistics for Brahmins, Buddhists&#xA;and Jains&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PROFESSOR ASHOK AKLUJKAR Professor of Sanskrit, Department of Asiun Studies,&#xA;University of British Columbia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Much writing has been done on the social and political aspects of the selection and use by Brahmins and Sramaņas of Sanskrit, Pāḷi and Prākr̥ta (particularly Ardha-māgadhi). Especially in the last few decades, Professor Madhav M. Deshpande has been very active in this area of research. With great effort and considerable awareness of the complexity of social life, he has tried to reconstruct the history of sociolinguistic relationships between the followers of the three major religions of ancient India. My paper, out of necessity, is principally a comment on the research of Deshpande (no one else has written on the subject as much as he has by keeping in view many different periods of Indian history), but since the more important of his assumptions are older and the more important of his conclusions have an affinity with what is currently accepted as historical truth in much of Indology, what I have to say is also a comment on Indology from the point of view of sociolinguistics as far as it pertains to the ancient period. In particular, I argue that the religiolinguistic universes of the Brahmins, Buddhists and Jains were more in harmony than has been assumed and that the use of Pāli and Ardha-māgadhi as languages of religious communication by the Buddhists and Jains was modeled after the use of Sanskrit by the Brahmins.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sanskrit as a supreme language - AA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/aklUjkaraH/aklUjkar_dominance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/aklUjkaraH/aklUjkar_dominance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sanskrit as a supreme language&amp;rdquo; by Ashok Aklujkar [&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/stream/paNDit-papers/AklujkarAEarlyHistorySktSuprem#page/n9/mode/2up&#34;&gt;Arch&lt;/a&gt;] is a very pertinent read. Some excerpts follow, with some added formatting. My notes are marked in bold like this: (&lt;strong&gt;VV: …&lt;/strong&gt;). The most important section is the one titled: &amp;ldquo;Emergence of dominance&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Languages very close to Sanskrit was spoken by nearly ALL classes of people in the first millennium BC [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/What-percentage-of-people-on-the-Indian-subcontinent-used-or-knew-Sanskrit-during-the-2nd-and-1st-millennium-BC&#34;&gt;Q13&lt;/a&gt;]. &amp;ldquo;The available evidence, from the earliest Sanskrit plays and other literary works around the time of the Buddha, is that Sanskrit and the early Prakrits were mutually intelligible. &amp;hellip; Pāṇini did indeed base his grammar on the speech of the &amp;ldquo;cultured&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;educated&amp;rdquo; (śiṣṭa) people, but the fact that his discussion (and the later one of Patañjali) includes idiomatic usage and much slang does indicate it was spoken for all purposes (i.e., including worldly everyday stuff) at least.&amp;rdquo; [खट्वारूढः, तीर्थध्वाङ्क्षः]&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Even svara-s were in use. People who travelled to the north and south banks of the vipAsha (उदक् च विपाशः॥ ४।२।७३ – &amp;ldquo;अञ् प्रत्ययो भवति चातुरर्थिकः। अणो ऽपवादः। … स्वरे विशेषः। महती सूक्ष्मेक्षिका वर्तते सूत्रकारस्य।&amp;rdquo;) (today’s Beas) river could hear that names of wells were pronounced differently, and pANini’s job was to describe it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sanskrit was not (contrary to popular misinformed opinion) a single dialect. It was the grammatically and phonetically standardized form of spoken late-Vedic. For there to exist a standardized form of the language, there should be multiple non-standard forms that are in use. The very existence of Pāṇini&amp;rsquo;s grammatical standard is itself the most potent proof of there having been multiple dialects of spoken sanskrit in the late-vedic period. The spoken dialects for which sanskrit grammar was composed can all be called sanskrit even though they did not obviously 100% agree grammatically or phonetically to the standard language in practice. Vestiges of these pre-standardized Old-Indic dialects survive from Indo-Aryan literature composed throughout the vedic period, particularly from the 5th-2nd centuries BCE (when a profusion of grammatical and phonetics texts were composed to standardize the spoken language). Vedic was not a single uniform dialect, it is the common name (umbrella term) given to several closely related spoken Indo-Iranian dialects of the Vedic period in South Asia (roughly 1500 BCE to 300 BCE).&amp;rdquo; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/d/msg/bvparishat/_w1ShqfczhY/27iVBdXsCQAJ&#34;&gt;BVP17&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;बहूनाम् साधारणवस्तूनां नामानि न दृश्यन्ते संस्कृते&amp;rdquo; इति हेत्वाभास एव। यतः सर्वेषु व्यवहारे दृश्यमानासु भाषासु सा दशा दृश्यते। शब्दानाम् आदानप्रदानम् आविष्कारश्च सहजाः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On the sanskrit/ prakrit/ apabhraMshA distinction - and its antiquity:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sanskrit literally means refined, prAkRt means natural/ innate (implying that it is not as polished/ standardized). This is analogous to the mArgii/ desii distinction in theater and dance.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There was non-uniformity in peoples&amp;rsquo; education (due to opportunity, circumstance and taste). Naurally, the more educated, scholarly class used more refined language, art and customs - owing to their expending a greater amount of effort in study, standardization and codification (whether it is in grammar, dance or music). Hence, the &amp;ldquo;sanskrit/ prakrit&amp;rdquo; distinction is quite old, predating even the buddha and the shramaNa-s.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;phases-of-sanskrit&#34;&gt;Phases of Sanskrit&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of the long time span I keep in view, the following would be the major divisions, if&lt;br&gt;&#xA;one were to follow the vicissitudes of Sanskrit as they have generally&lt;br&gt;&#xA;been seen in the scholarship on the subject:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
