<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;देशपाण्डेय-माधवः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/articles/deshapANDeya-mAdhavaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;देशपाण्डेय-माधवः on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/articles/deshapANDeya-mAdhavaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1986: Facets of morphology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/articles/deshapANDeya-mAdhavaH/1986-Some-Facets-of-pANinian-Morphology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/articles/deshapANDeya-mAdhavaH/1986-Some-Facets-of-pANinian-Morphology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1986&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MADHAV M. DESHPANDE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SOME FACETS OF PĀŅINIAN MORPHOLOGY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-basic-morphological-categories&#34;&gt;1. Basic Morphological Categories&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pāṇini&amp;rsquo;s - Aştādhyāyi makes a clear terminological distinction between prātipadika &amp;rsquo;nominal stem&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;dhātu &amp;lsquo;verb root&amp;rsquo; and pratyaya ‘affix&amp;rsquo;. It can be shown that these three are most probably the ultimate three classes of Pāņini&amp;rsquo;s morphology. The preliminary proof of such a proposition may be presented as follows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pāņini defines dhātu &amp;lsquo;verb root&amp;rsquo; by referring to his list of these items, viz. P.1.3.1 (bhūvādayo dhātavaḥ) which basically says: &amp;lsquo;bhū etc. (as they are listed in the appendix called Dhātupātha) are given the designation dhātu.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orality to writing</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/articles/deshapANDeya-mAdhavaH/From-Orality-to-Writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/articles/deshapANDeya-mAdhavaH/From-Orality-to-Writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From Orality to Writing: Transmission and  Interpretation of Pāṇini’s Aṣṭādhyāyī&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MADHAV M. DESHPANDE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-emergence-of-writing&#34;&gt;1. Emergence of writing&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Emergence of writing in ancient India and Pāṇini’s knowledge  and /or use of writing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the last two decades, extensive research has appeared dealing  with the origin of scripts in ancient India, and the chief participants in  this research, namely Harry FALK, Oskar von HINÜBER, and Richard  SALOMON, have not only discussed the question of the origin of  Kharoṣṭhī and Brāhmī script, but have also considered available literary  references in the ancient Indian literature that have been taken by the  various authorities to infer an awareness of the art of writing. This  includes references in the Aṣṭādhyāyī of Pāṇini. Pāṇini knows the word  lipi, which conventionally refers to script, and teaches (cf. P. 3.2.21)  the formation of the term lipikara, along with libikara, both presumably  in the sense of scribes or writers. In another rule (cf. P. 4.1.49), Pāṇini  teaches the derivation of the feminine formation yavanānī, and according  to Kātyāyana’s Vārttika (yavanāl lipyām), this formation refers to the  script of the Yavanas. Oskar von HINÜBER (1989: 57) suggests the  meaning of “painter” for the term lipikara, but given the later Sanskrit  use of lipi in the sense of script, and the Old Persian cognate dipi in the  same sense, it seems most likely that Pāṇini was aware of some form  of script used in his vicinity. The most likely scripts in the vicinity are  Aramaic and Greek, attested in Aśokan inscriptions in the Gandhāran  area, shortly after Pāṇini. While there seems to be an emerging  consensus that Brāhmī is a Mauryan invention, it appears that there  may have been earlier forms of Kharoṣṭhī in existence in that area for  some time before the Mauryas, and, while there is no direct evidence to support this claim, Pāṇini may have been familiar with some of these  early forms of Kharoṣṭhī, along with awareness of scripts like Aramaic  and Greek. Richard SALOMON (1998: 11ff) has reviewed the earlier  debate regarding Pāṇini’s awareness of some form of script, and he sees  “no reason to rule out Kharoṣṭhī which therefore may well date back  to the mid-fourth century B.C. or quite possibly even earlier” (p. 13).  However, even if we were to assume that some earlier form of Kharoṣṭhī  was known to Pāṇini, based on our knowledge of the earliest attested  forms of this script we can conclude that such an early form of Kharoṣṭhī  would only be approximate orthography (e.g., geminates represented  by single consonants, vowel length left unmarked) for Sanskrit, and  would be largely inadequate to capture the complex oral features of  Pāṇini’s Aṣṭādhyāyī. In a personal communication to me, SALOMON  says: “Anyway, by the time of Patañjali, i.e. 2nd century B.C. (?), neither  Brāhmī and Kharoṣṭhī had developed the sort of refinements that would  permit the texts concerned to be recorded in full detail – or rather, that  is how it looks on the basis of the epigraphic record, which however is  no doubt far from the whole story – it is merely the part of the story that  we have, and a rather sparsely documented one for this period for that  matter. I find it quite plausible that by Patañjali’s time Sanskrit could  be written quite adequately, though probably not perfectly, in either  script”. SALOMON appropriately reminds us that even the later scripts  do not represent Pāṇini’s metalanguage perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
