<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>3 1 Challenges</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/3_1_Challenges1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/3_1_Challenges1/</guid>
      <description>[1]: In this chapter, and in the following chapters, I will not provide anuvr̥tta ‘continued’ terms in brackets (unless necessary), even though I did this in the previous chapters.
In the previous chapter, I introduced my solution to the problem of rule interaction at the same step. In this chapter, I will discuss the relationship of my solution with other aspects of the functioning of the Aṣṭādhyāyī.
Let us look at two examples of DOI from nominal inflection which pose a challenge to my interpretation of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 2 DOI in the Inflection of Taddhita, Samāsa and Kr̥danta Nominal Bases</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/3_2_DOI_in_the_Inflection_of_Taddhita_samAsa_and_K/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/3_2_DOI_in_the_Inflection_of_Taddhita_samAsa_and_K/</guid>
      <description>So far, we have looked at cases of DOI in the inflection of simple (i.e., underived) nominal bases (cf. 1.2.45 arthavad adhātur apratyayaḥ prātipadikam). Now let us look at some cases of DOI in the inflection of complex (i.e., derived) nominal bases such as kr̥t ‘primary derivative’, taddhita ‘secondary derivative’, and samāsa ‘compound’ (cf. 1.2.46 kr̥ttaddhitasamāsāś ca).
Generally speaking, as compared to the inflection of simple nominal bases, which we have seen in the previous chapter and in this chapter, and verbal inflection and primary derivatives, which we will see in the following chapters, we find a smaller number of examples of conflict in taddhita derivations, and even fewer examples in samāsa derivations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 3 SOI in Taddhita derivations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/3_3_SOI_in_Taddhita_derivations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/vyAkaraNam/pANinIyam/paribhAShA/articles/vipratiShedhe_param/shabda-paratva-thesis_riShi-rAj-popat/03/3_3_SOI_in_Taddhita_derivations/</guid>
      <description>The cases of SOI which we find in samāsa derivations are few and fairly simple. I will not be discussing them in this thesis. In taddhita derivations, we come across examples of SOI between rules teaching affixation. Consider the derivation of autsa ‘male offspring of utsa’ (cf. 4.1.92 tasyāpatyam ‘his offspring’). Three rules teach the addition of three different affixes:
4.1.83 prāg dīvyato’ṇ: the taddhita affix aṆ is added to denote senses taught in rules from here up to 4.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
